<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>bto-pro</title>
  <link href="https://btopro.com/atom.xml" rel="self" />
  <subtitle>Loud, yelly, abrasive, caring; dreaming the future into reality.</subtitle>
  <updated>2019-10-11T08:09:54-06:00</updated>
  <author>
      <name>Bryan Ollendyke</name>
  </author>
  <id>https://btopro.com/feed</id>
  <entry>
    <title>The infinite void</title>
    <id>https://btopro.com/the-infinite-void</id>
    <updated>2019-10-16T20:14:54-06:00</updated>
    <published>2019-10-16T19:37:39-06:00</published>
    <summary>Staring off, into nothing. Spacing out, focusing on the sound and the feeling of the sun beating down on my arms. I don't know what it is.. but when I see others relax at the beach I can't help but fe</summary>
    <link href="https://btopro.com/the-infinite-void"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>Staring off, into nothing. Spacing out, focusing on the sound and the feeling of the sun beating down on my arms. I don't know what it is.. but when I see others relax at the beach I can't help but feel like everyone's missing out on the nothing around them; tasting the surface level pleasures of the place and missing the deeper meaning in front of them.</p>
<p>The infinite. The stillness. I love the feeling of being nothing; a tiny spec of sand that the ocean would bowl over and the heat would melt were I only to stand there long enough. The connection with nature and centering myself seem to always align, yet I never notice till I'm in that moment.</p>
<p>To touch and climb on rocks worn over several million years. The waves crashing against them, wearing small holes and sharp points in them. These senses are what I long for and fall out of consciousness when I get to experience.</p>
<p>They cause me to lose track of my thoughts, my mind wanders freely and to exploration over the next commit to push. I push forward in the cove not because I know what'll be at the end but because I want to see what'll be along the way.</p>
<p>I swam with my wife out to a small coral reef just beyond where we could easily stand and were greeted by many striped fish that swam so close I felt them bump into me multiple times. My hands pulling aside the water that they so effortlessly live in, it was one of those objective-less journeys that I need to fully reset.</p>
<p>And I have. 1/2 way through our vacation, I have fully reset. And the reason I know I have is that vacations always start out and I'm exhausted. Happy to just be sleeping, eating, and not thinking. I had the luxury of getting access to a Sauna and steam room which I continue to meditate and oscillate between frequently.</p>
<p>It's been great for clearing my head and resting my brain... but it's nothing compared to swimming and chasing fish. The unknown. Peering through a rock sliced by the weather to see whats on the other side.. *sigh*. I'm still here writing from the deck and I dream of going back.</p>
<p>There's often a prize in exploring the unknown. Sure, I have no idea if there are sharks here or where jelly fish are, and those thoughts cross my mind as to why no one else is pushing out into the waters I was wading.</p>
<p>But while pushing forward cautiously, not knowing what I'd find while snorkeling, I saw a fish the size of my chest. A gorgeous shimmering blue and green fish that I then followed along. It was amazing to see up close and wanting to keep my distance a bit to not scare it away. Watching it feed on rocks in the cove and then being able to watch it from shore 30 yards away later because of how clear the water was... I won't soon forget it.</p>
<p>I am reset once again by the infinite void. The ocean. Calling me back to be re-centered. I know the climb I've been on this year has been more insane then usual. I know my family, understanding as they are, have suffered by my lack of being there mentally even if I have been there physically.</p>
<p>I'm grateful to have this opportunity of solace just my wife and I. I'm happy for my boys knowing that when I return to them I will be fully focused on them. I'm no longer burned at both ends, borrowing time from all sides to plug the holes in my leaky schedule.</p>
<p>I need to take more time like this in smaller doses to just travel into the woods and take the boys for a bike ride or a walk. They need the full me and I apparently need nature far more than I realize. Stillness. Wholeness.</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why I started hax-camp</title>
    <id>https://btopro.com/why-i-started-hax-camp</id>
    <updated>2019-10-16T19:38:53-06:00</updated>
    <published>2019-09-11T12:12:51-06:00</published>
    <summary>Hi. I'm Bryan Ollendyke, and I have a vision of the future and, I think, a way to get there. I'm not fancy. I don't have big money. I don't have important people on high; I have something far more imp</summary>
    <link href="https://btopro.com/why-i-started-hax-camp"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[  ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>My first time on stage</title>
    <id>https://btopro.com/my-first-time-on-stage</id>
    <updated>2019-10-16T19:38:53-06:00</updated>
    <published>2019-08-29T13:09:43-06:00</published>
    <summary>This, is probably going to become a weekly thing or at least I'll try and make it one. This is a recap of the 1st week of class with #EdTechJoker.If you haven't followed the references, I'm code na</summary>
    <link href="https://btopro.com/my-first-time-on-stage"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[  ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Annabella</title>
    <id>https://btopro.com/annabella</id>
    <updated>2019-10-16T19:38:53-06:00</updated>
    <published>2019-07-27T21:34:02-06:00</published>
    <summary>The wheels squeaked on the cart, boosting my kid sister I placed her in the front part kids sit in. Five years old, happy to have someone who could lift her high. I was fifteen when we went to a rando</summary>
    <link href="https://btopro.com/annabella"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[  ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hey, remember when</title>
    <id>https://btopro.com/hey-remember-when</id>
    <updated>2019-10-16T19:38:53-06:00</updated>
    <published>2019-07-21T18:45:49-06:00</published>
    <summary>A couch. It had to be the couch. The bastard scurries away, unheeding in the warnings of the past weeks. Undeterred in his quest for one thing. One, insatiable goal.To build a nest, in my &#34;Effing&#34; co</summary>
    <link href="https://btopro.com/hey-remember-when"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[  ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Open Community Pedagogy</title>
    <id>https://btopro.com/open-community-pedagogy</id>
    <updated>2019-10-16T19:38:53-06:00</updated>
    <published>2019-06-21T09:07:22-06:00</published>
    <summary>  This instructional designer didn't need to know HTML in order to convey an instructional concept.  Your right! No one should need to understand HTML in order to contribute meaningful knowledge to t</summary>
    <link href="https://btopro.com/open-community-pedagogy"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[  ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Stand against the ocean</title>
    <id>https://btopro.com/stand-against-the-ocean-2</id>
    <updated>2019-10-16T19:38:53-06:00</updated>
    <published>2019-06-19T14:40:55-06:00</published>
    <summary>The waves of life will crash upon you, and they'll crash hard my son. You'll be expected to carry loads that you feel aren't yours. You'll be asked to stand when it's so much easier to sit. You'll be</summary>
    <link href="https://btopro.com/stand-against-the-ocean-2"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <meme-maker style="width: 75%; margin: 0px auto; display: block;" image-url="files/scale-50/IMG_20190307_142300.jpg" top-text="Stand Against" bottom-text="Complacency" imageurl="files/scale-50/IMG_20190307_142300.jpg" toptext="Stop what your doing" bottomtext="Stand and be counted" dataeditable="" datahaxray="Meme"></meme-maker>
<p>The waves of life will crash upon you, and they'll crash hard my son. You'll be expected to carry loads that you feel aren't yours. You'll be asked to stand when it's so much easier to sit. You'll be expected to behave, when rebellion is necessary.</p>
<p>When they tell you to sit, these forces of complacency, know that with each passing wave, you drift further from the goal back to shore. When we sit by the waters edge, deciding whether to wade into uncharted territory, we're hit with relentlessly strong currents.</p>
<p>The water seeks to pull us down to the depth below. To consume those that enter the unknown. If we step into the waters a few inches, get concerns and then merely sit still, we have to face the force of the crashing wave.</p>
<p>These waves are far stronger than we realize, each crash lifting you off your seat and shifting you back ever slightly, sometimes so little that we hardly notice. But rest assured, you are being pushed backward. If you sit long enough, the waves will push you back till your nearly on dry land; the journey over.</p>
<p>If you stand though, you'll be hit by those heavy waves. And you must be, for if not broken against the waves we harden and are made stronger. For we are anti-fragile my child. We were born to be strengthen with each passing wave.</p>
<p>If we step forward in between these waves, never ceasing, never resting but to achieve eternity, then we will be where we want to in this world. Out beyond the currents, beyond the waters of today. Stand my child and cut through the waves.</p>
<h2 class="hax-active">Be different.</h2>
<p>Be abnormal. <span style="font-size: var(--haxcms-base-styles-p-font-size, 24px); letter-spacing: var(--haxcms-base-styles-p-letter-spacing, 0.5px); caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">Be Bold. Live Free. Burn Bright. Never back down. Never surrender. Never let anyone tell you who you are not, show them who you are.</span></p>
<p>For if we all stand and cut through the waves, they become increasingly less difficult. The deeper the water gets, the less impactful the crashing of the waves.</p>
<p>And we may yet be able to swim to the brighter shores across the chasm we've been told exists but was never the reality.</p>
<hr style="width: 50%;"/><video-player accent-color="deep-purple" iframed="iframed" is-a11y-media="is-a11y-media" is-youtube="is-youtube" lang="en" media-title="The humbling river" preload="metadata" source="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=O0YxeTjFn70" source-type="youtube" sticky-corner="top-right" youtube-id="O0YxeTjFn70" resource="#2a70bb89-4959-afee-809a" prefix="oer:http://oerschema.org/ schema:http://schema.org/ dc:http://purl.org/dc/terms/ foaf:http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/ cc:http://creativecommons.org/ns# bib:http://bib.schema.org " sources="[]" tracks="[]" schema-resource-id="#2a70bb89-4959-afee-809a"></video-player>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>EdTechJoker</title>
    <id>https://btopro.com/edtechjoker-2</id>
    <updated>2019-10-16T19:38:53-06:00</updated>
    <published>2019-06-12T20:14:21-06:00</published>
    <summary>Ex Plures PluresFrom many, many. The phrase of a new publishing revolution.I'm old enough to remember old me. Oh, that guy. So tired. So broken. So lost. So disaffected. But the guy that showed up a</summary>
    <link href="https://btopro.com/edtechjoker-2"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>Ex Plures Plures</p>
<p>From many, many. The phrase of a new publishing revolution.</p>
<p>I'm old enough to remember old me. Oh, that guy. So tired. So broken. So lost. So disaffected. But the guy that showed up at Domains19. That spoke with a burning passion about what he's doing, why he's doing it, and without fear. That guy is working towards who I want to be.</p>
<p>Sustaining momentum is a difficult beast in software projects, especially passion and mission driven ones. It takes recognition that hundreds of hours of work. Sleepless nights, broken builds, mis-named variables, enter and escape key pushes, all culminate in 5 minutes if your lucky, 5 seconds more than likely.</p>
<p>All that work. All that lost sleep, often the pain of which is detailed here in specific posts about losing time with my children to pursuit what I've been made to do, the person I want them to proud of some day.... boils down to those few minutes.</p>
<p>I've had "shots" before, times when I said "yes, this is it. this is the moment that people will understand the picture in my head. I'll explain it right <i>this</i>

 time. <b>This time they'll get it</b>

." A false fairytale that you'll ever wake up from; a scene in a movie and say there's the scene that they "made it".</p>
<p>Last year around this time is a perfect example; presenting to a New York based audience about HAX. Money to solve problems, audience receptive to headless solutions; and me with a system that gobbled our presenters content just hours before the talk. A tech demo blow up prior to what would be a tech talk disaster.</p>
<p>The co-presenters thought it went fine and talking to people after they generally got it. But I didn't want "generally got it". I wanted effect, impact, realization. And there I was.. with a broken "solution" projecting an alternative view of reality that didn't just look half baked but was.</p>
<p>It was painful. Really. deeply painful. To realize that I wasn't there yet. That I still had nothing to show for all my sleeplessness. I did another talk the next week and it was fine, much better but I didn't seek it to have this impact. I knew I had over hyped myself as to what would happen.</p>
<p>After those, I shifted gears to process. We shifted to internal workflow and process that needed realigned if we would ever make it there. It was demoralizing work; at times copy and paste, run a job that had to pass on 180 project repos in an unknown configuration taking upwards of an hour to process, failing if it didn't get every single one. We didn't know what we were doing, we just knew we had to regroup code organization wise.</p>
<p>But after two months, and having a process that appeared to finally be correct. I began the hard work of converting and normalizing all of our elements, our labor that was well intentioned but slightly off course if it would ever hit the quality standards of a production project / product.</p>
<p>I took a week several months ago and just normalized some doc blocks, some placement of basic syntax, demos, all the nitty gritty.</p>
<p>There are hundreds of hours. Painful, hours, that go into being able to pull off where we are now, and where we'll get to from here. It's all for those 5 minutes, those 5 seconds.</p>
<p>But to hear that spark. Those eyes light up. To see another human being you don't know or have just met connect with your work, your vision, for the first time... that's what I live for. I live for changing minds, teaching, helping empower others.</p>
<p>I have a very supportive wife and family; friends and colleagues too, all that I love. They got me through that darkness by believing that what I was saying was possible and picked me up either through coffee or venting or a drink after work or a goal on the hockey rink. They helped keep me from my darker parts.</p>
<p>But those new eyes. Those delights, those people we unplug form the matrix of what was. They aren't people I know. They aren't sold based on knowing me. They sometimes aren't deeply technical.</p>
<video-player accent-color="deep-purple" iframed is-a11y-media is-youtube lang="en" media-title="HAXTheWeb: Chaotic good" preload="metadata" source="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Eksr9y4nxQ4" sources="[]" source-type="youtube" sticky-corner="top-right" tracks="[]" youtube-id="Eksr9y4nxQ4" resource="#38020ce8-4c27-cdc1-9060" prefix="oer:http://oerschema.org/ schema:http://schema.org/ dc:http://purl.org/dc/terms/ foaf:http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/ cc:http://creativecommons.org/ns# bib:http://bib.schema.org "></video-player>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Technical weapons</title>
    <id>https://btopro.com/technical-weapons</id>
    <updated>2019-10-16T19:38:53-06:00</updated>
    <published>2019-06-05T20:51:23-06:00</published>
    <summary>Labels often set the narrative, or so liberals would argue. It's why they express deep concerns about the ways language is formed. Language can be used to divide, debate, and ensure that certain peopl</summary>
    <link href="https://btopro.com/technical-weapons"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[  ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I made a thing</title>
    <id>https://btopro.com/i-made-a-thing</id>
    <updated>2019-10-16T19:38:54-06:00</updated>
    <published>2019-05-31T15:01:29-06:00</published>
    <summary>Hey hey, ho ho. Welcome. To the revolution!!Come say hi at Apereo 2019 or Domains 2019.</summary>
    <link href="https://btopro.com/i-made-a-thing"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[  ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>THE web components high performance video</title>
    <id>https://btopro.com/the-web-components-high-performance-video-2</id>
    <updated>2019-10-16T19:38:54-06:00</updated>
    <published>2019-05-24T08:56:35-06:00</published>
    <summary>I've become a bit performance obsessed. I often lament that the worst part of working on something you are passionate about is that first impressions with the software are everything and that if someo</summary>
    <link href="https://btopro.com/the-web-components-high-performance-video-2"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>I've become a bit performance obsessed. I often lament that the worst part of working on something you are passionate about is that first impressions with the software are everything and that if someone isn't hooked visually in about 5 seconds, you're not going to get them interested in your work.</p>
<p>To that end, I've been performance obsessed in web components, <a href="https://haxtheweb.org/">HAXTheWeb</a>
, and all server configuration areas. I was able to take our scores previously from pretty bad to decent on Google Lighthouse, just by making some tweaks to how things rendered, timing, etc.</p>
<p>I neglected one factor in all my previous testing though... I wasn't actually using a live, running, out there in the open web server. It was always local development or github pages, which can only go so far on their own. I expected to get the same results when I pushed things up to a live server and ran some tests. Boy was I wrong...</p>
<h2>It was even faster in production!</h2>
<img src="files/scale-50/2019-05-24_11-14-49.jpg" alt="Insanely high scores on Google's Lighthouse appliance to demonstrate performance of up coming project." style="width: 100%; margin: 0px auto; display: block;"/><p>These rather insane scores are showing an upcoming <a href="https://github.com/elmsln/haxiam">SaaS version of HAXcms</a>
 that I'm currently building. Other team members reactions to playing with the SaaS offering recently have ranged from "I love you" to "I can't believe it's this far along" to "why is it this fast? This is stupid fast" to utter disbelief.</p>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/hey__mp">@hey__mp</a>
 opened our test site on his phone, on rural wifi (so DSL, and not good DSL) and had the site in 1 second. This HAXcms in production, is stupid fast. I decided to shoot a video talking about how we were able to achieve these stupidly fast scores given the following constraints we intentionally place on ourselves:</p>
<ul><li>We do not bundle assets, we ship ES6 modules / AMD directly to browsers</li>



<li>IE11 / things outside of ES6 window are shipped a watered down design</li>


<li>Users must click through a UI and build a site much like they would in a CMS context, yet the system produce a high scoring offline capable PWA (so no developers hands in the PWA construction)</li>


<li>We do not do server side rendering, it's all client side processed</li>


<li>All decisions are made to ensure HAXcms micro-sites can run with or without HAXcms as part of our publishing methodology (so all sites are decentralizable / copy and paste capable and run anywhere)</li>


</ul>
<p><span style="caret-color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">So given these constrains,... how the hell were we able to achieve these scores? I encourage you to watch and find out.</span></p>
<video-player accent-color="lime" dark="dark" iframed="" is-a11y-media="" is-youtube="" lang="en" media-title="Crazy deep performance walk through with HAXcms" preload="metadata" source="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7o8T1eymTnQ" source-type="youtube" sticky-corner="top-right" youtube-id="7o8T1eymTnQ" resource="#3e3cee5f-bc3f-b445-8b9f" prefix="oer:http://oerschema.org/ schema:http://schema.org/ dc:http://purl.org/dc/terms/ foaf:http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/ cc:http://creativecommons.org/ns# bib:http://bib.schema.org " sources="[]" tracks="[]"></video-player>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ocean</title>
    <id>https://btopro.com/ocean</id>
    <updated>2019-10-16T19:38:54-06:00</updated>
    <published>2019-05-03T12:21:19-06:00</published>
    <summary>Now and then, life feels like your adrift in an ocean of work on a sinking ship. There's water so choppy that it feels like you can't see land off in the distance let alone dream of swimming there. Th</summary>
    <link href="https://btopro.com/ocean"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[  ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Drunken UX interview</title>
    <id>https://btopro.com/drunken-ux-interview-2</id>
    <updated>2019-10-16T19:38:54-06:00</updated>
    <published>2019-04-01T11:47:45-06:00</published>
    <summary>I was recently interviewed on the Drunken UX podcast, a show about all things web and user experience design. I was there to talk web components, block editors, and of course #HAXTheWeb</summary>
    <link href="https://btopro.com/drunken-ux-interview-2"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>I was recently interviewed on the <a href="https://drunkenux.com/podcast/33-hax-the-planet/">Drunken UX podcast</a>












, a show about all things web and user experience design. I was there to talk web components, block editors, and of course <a href="https://haxtheweb.org/">#HAXTheWeb</a>









.</p>
<p><br/></p>
<p>The conversation steered into the advantages of web components over past technology solutions and libraries and is a really good consolidation of a lot of my thoughts about web components and their importance in building a more sustainable, open web. Half way through we turn to HAX and I'm left open to rant... (so I do)</p>
<p>I'd like to unpack a statement because I realize that while I did an ok job of explaining it, I'd like to have it written down if it end sup coming up. I said something intentionally controversial because if we don't challenge those with power, regardless of their intention, then we are left accepting powerlessness as a feature instead of the bug that it is.</p>
<h2>The quote</h2>
<p>The takes place at 44:41 remaining in the show. <a href="https://drunkenux.com/podcast/">Please subscribe to, rate and review their podcast</a>












 but I wanted to link to the audio here in context in case you wanted to listen to it while reading why I feel this way.</p>
<paper-audio-player src="https://episodes.drunkenux.com/drunkenux/dux-e33.mp3" title="#33: HAX the Planet!" preload="auto" current-time="4036.446044" time-left="5387.833469" small-skip="15" large-skip="60" role="application" aria-label="Audio Player" aria-describedby="title" accent-color="purple" resource="#7b05d228-7263-fb95-435e" prefix="oer:http://oerschema.org/ schema:http://schema.org/ dc:http://purl.org/dc/terms/ foaf:http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/ cc:http://creativecommons.org/ns# bib:http://bib.schema.org " style="width: 75%; margin: 0px auto; display: block;"></paper-audio-player>
<lrndesign-blockquote citation="04/01/2019" image="files/crop-sm/IMG_20190127_153429.jpg" author="btopro" display-mode="leather" resource="#f2d9bcf3-7000-eacb-cf69" prefix="oer:http://oerschema.org/ schema:http://schema.org/ dc:http://purl.org/dc/terms/ foaf:http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/ cc:http://creativecommons.org/ns# bib:http://bib.schema.org " style="width: 100%; margin: 0px auto; display: block;">  <span>I see Gutenberg as a<br/>
<strong>direct existential threat</strong>












 to the open web [and OER].</span></lrndesign-blockquote>
<p>So this critique is not of the people who work on Gutenberg. It is a deeper philosophical question of trust and control in open source and the open web. When I say do you trust Matt. I don't mean as a person, I mean do you trust one person with control of your entire UX, forever.</p>
<p>It's a fair comparison to say the same could be lodged at me in designing HAX; and yes I am aware other people have worked on Gutenberg (and HAX has more then just me on it...). My primary criticisms grouped:</p>
<h2 class="hax-active">Sustainability</h2>
<p>React is the flavor of this five year segment of time and we're coming up on its end. Being from Drupal I saw core developers jump on javascript trains that had already fallen out of favor by the time they deployed. This will not be the case with web components. Web components are in the browser you're viewing this on. They aren't going away.</p>
<p>You may say "But React isn't going away" and that's reasonable. But I mean... jQuery didn't go anywhere... so why did we all move away from it for these advanced platforms? It's all "just" javascript right?</p>
<p>React's destiny is pegged to Facebook's desire for it; which means WordPress will have to keep pace with where they take that community. I don't view this as long term sustainable. Will a WordPress site site, without being touched, and still function correctly 10 years from now when needing to update the Gutenblocks as well as surrounding JS library ecosystem?</p>
<p>HAX output no longer requires HAX. Content pulled into HAX is just reading DOM and then processing it. We can disappear tomorrow and our elements will still work. Since we treat the DOM as an API, we will continue to expand it at a rate that far outpaces Gutenberg.</p>
<h2 class="hax-active">A story</h2>
<p>Our components work anywhere, with or without HAX. We make a public website (like this one you're viewing). As part of the build we make a new card element. It can go from usage on this website to generalized, HAX capable element in about 5 minutes. The web expands our platform, not WordPress. WordPress (Drupal too) will never keep pace with our expansion just given this fact.</p>
<p>As we build the web, we build up the base of legos for all of it. Not just specific pockets of it.</p>
<p>Accessibility</p>
<p>Gutenberg and accessibility have had a rocky time out of the gate. Learning React, just to participate in accessibility testing is a non-starter. We keep our web components compiled but not bundled in part for this reason. Anyone can run an accessibility audit on something we make, find the element in the DOM that wraps what failed, and make a report. They can also see the file it came from and trace it back to the source; which what they'll find...looks...like...html.</p>
<p>This may seem petty but it's not. We're actually at odds with the web component community standards (which is to roll things like Webpack / bundlers to reduce assets delivered). It's more important to us that anyone can find, diagnose, and remix what we're doing, and the traceability by the average web professional (not WP pro + React pro) is critical to long term sustainability.</p>
<p>HAX also originates in higher education, where we have <i><b>legal</b>











</i>











 and ethical responsibilities to generate, maintain and improve the accessibility of what we produce. Web components represent an immense opportunity for us to generate a more open and accessible web as a result of remix.</p>
<h2 class="hax-active">Power consolidation</h2>
<p>Please don't confuse charity with corporate interests. "OH THANK YOU FOR THIS EDITOR"... which you only produced because you need to in order to try and go after markets like Wix and Squarespace. The goal isn't democratizing the web anymore, it's consolidating power under one banner. Non-conspiratorially, the less people that understand the authoring experience of WordPress, the more business for WordPress.com and vendor space.</p>
<p>Our component library is highly readable, has tooling (and soon front end assets) to completely automate the writing of the wiring for our editor. Editor outputs are no longer tied to the editor; we seek a great rebalancing of the powers of the web. HAX has ties into multiple CMS ecosystems already and can easily be ported over to others.</p>
<p>Yes, we're building a "CMS" to manage pages because the editor eliminates the vast majority of needs for database driven anything. Yes, I'll continue to criticize database backed solutions (while still having to maintain my own slew of them). However, HAXcms will be completely built out of open and reusable components that aside from our theme scaffolding will make sense in other solutions (that are non-HAX). We are actively tearing down power structures in the methodologies by which we are approaching development.</p>
<p>We publish all our components to webcomponents.org, a public, non-CMS specific location. I've seen talk of WP having its own Blocks catalog, which makes sense... but again, why consolidate UX discovery to one ecosystem. Why develop for a single ecosystem when you can improve the web holistically?</p>
<h2>Not being a jerk.</h2>
<p>Gutenberg is a fantastic idea with a lot of effort and resources and sleepless nights poured into it. It will empower people to produce things and is open source and those are great things. I think it threatens long term sustainability, accessibility, and development interest. I think web components provide a unique opportunity to tear down the power silos we've all built over the last decade.</p>
<p>You shouldn't need someone else in order to present yourself online. It shouldn't cost you anything. You should have total ownership and control over your information. It shouldn't be tied to any platform beyond the browser itself.</p>
<p>We have a unique opportunity to ensure that happens. <span style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">Don't throw your efforts into a single silo that will let you down.</span></p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>All screens have rights</title>
    <id>https://btopro.com/all-screens-have-rights-2</id>
    <updated>2019-10-16T19:38:54-06:00</updated>
    <published>2019-03-28T09:24:37-06:00</published>
    <summary>The EU recently passed Article 13, which it's still too early to tell the implications of but it's troubling to say the least. Any time people start trying to legislate 1s and 0s I get concerned</summary>
    <link href="https://btopro.com/all-screens-have-rights-2"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>The <a href="https://www.engadget.com/2019/03/26/european-parliament-copyright-directive-article-13/">EU recently passed Article 13</a>





, which it's still too early to tell the implications of but it's troubling to say the least. Any time people start trying to legislate 1s and 0s I get concerned; namely, because their interests are in direct competition with those of their citizens (governments enjoy having major international enterprises they can sue to fill their coffers after all).</p>
<p>That whole thing had me thinking about access to information and the ideas of <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2013/01/13/technology/aaron-swartz-internet-activist-dies-at-26.html">Aaron Swartz</a>





; namely that information seeks to be free. In the years since Aaron's unfortunate death, we've seen silicon valley accelerate in its quest to put up barriers to the free flow of information in the name of a new enemy: User Experience.</p>
<p>Facebook: "We have the best experiences, and so you should <i><b>share</b>





</i>





 all your content here without thinking about it"<br/>Twitter: "We have the fastest experience, so you should <i><b>share</b>





</i>





 your stream of consciousness here without thinking about it"<br/>Medium: "We have the best writing experience, so you should share your ideas here while working them out."<br/></p>
<p>These platforms. These digital silos, do empower people to share and have a voice. But they are antithetical to the open content and open access vision that Aaron is often credited with.</p>
<p>I was passed along some links recently related to <a href="https://indieweb.org/">Indieweb</a>





 and <a href="https://ioo.coop/">The Internet of Ownership</a>





, and it got me thinking. HAX and HAXcms are in this sphere of local control, better control, better tools, more access to those tools, but I haddn't really thought through the additional technical requirements not talked about in that pursuit. Namely, that every screen has a right to content.</p>
<h2 class="hax-active">Extending the vision of Information seeks to be Free</h2>
<p>Every screen you possess has a right to access content. If you are connected to the internet, there should be no barriers between that screen and web based HTML data structures... otherwise known as all information that exists on the internet.</p>
<p>Every site you access adopts the web platform standards.. with a catch.</p>
<h3 class="hax-active">Click here to upgrade your app?</h3>
<p><i>Not using Chrome? Click here to switch</i>





</p>
<p><i>You appear to be using an outdated browser, please upgrade.</i>





</p>
<p>Now look, upgrading, and modernizing with the web are nice. Helpful especially to the developer. But if we as developers</p>
<p>Every screens have a right to content. The internet has given birth to incredible communications possibilities (duh). But in that rise, we've seen an ebb and flow as far as access to content, ideas and media. Facebook, twitter and others require you to use updated devices and software in order to access their platform.</p>
<h3>I'm sorry let's reframe that</h3>
<p>Facebook, twitter and others require you to upgrade and pay additional monies for modern, fancy devices, <b>in order to read and express ideas with one another.</b>





</p>
<p>The platforms require you to use them and manipulate you into using them more. They connect you to people but at a price; that you will always connect through them. One of the major methods of dissolving decentralized individual ownership of the web was by killing RSS.</p>
<p>Google played a huge role in this through killing it's podcasting platform; and not that they controlled the universe in this regard, but it forced content producers to think of other ways of doing syndication. Namely, through Google and Apple app stores.</p>
<h2 class="hax-active">We want to bring the old web back</h2>
<p>And here's the plan. Beyond just HAX and HAXcms, its important to realize the philosophical design decisions that have now been baked into the HAXcms platform which I'll list as features in headings below.</p>
<h3 class="hax-active">Automatic RSS and Atom feed generation</h3>
<p>RSS and Atom allow sites to share updates about what's been produced. It is (an old) format that is a pure form of notifying others sites about your latest postings and work. HAXcms now automatically generates these data feeds and then provides buttons for designers that automatically wire them up. This will let more people start publishing in these formats without having to think about it or know they exist.</p>
<h3 class="hax-active">Automatic sitemap / robots generation</h3>
<p>For search engines to find you, you need good SEO. HAXcms outputs with SEO best practices automatically baked into the platform. Again, you shouldn't have to think about getting high search rankings in order to do it. It should just happen.</p>
<h3 class="hax-active">Automatic Offline / lack of internet usage</h3>
<p>All HAXcms sites are what is known as "Progressive Web Apps" (PWA). A PWA can leverage modern browser techniques to allow users to install your website on their phone (or laptop), which improves performance and makes reading more enjoyable. Also, if a user has been to your website (installed or not) and loses internet connection, they'll still have access to all of the content of your site (minus things like remotely loaded images / links to other websites). This ensures a high quality experience even when internet is of low quality (big for rural, low income, mass transit or otherwise lacking in data connection users).</p>
<h3 class="hax-active">Support for all screens</h3>
<p>This was a tricky one. HAXcms is now able to deliver to all platforms of the web going back to <i>IE6 / FF 3 / Safari 4</i>




, possibly even earlier. For reference, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_Explorer_6">IE6 is 20 years old</a>

 . In order to achieve this, we've implemented a (brilliant) progressive enhancement strategy that works like so:</p>
<ul><li>Modern / evergreen? You get the highest quality, fastest method of shipping assets to you (~85% traffic)</li>





<li>Slightly behind / off version? You get the same quality, slightly slower to load (ES5 versions, still works great tho. ~8% traffic)</li>


<li>Edge / semi-modern but not web components native platforms - You get an alternate experience though still web components (~4%)</li>





<li>IE 6 - 11 / Anything made in the last 20 years, or has javascript disabled (~3% or less). You get an iframe / dramatically simplified version of the site. Web components in content won't work, but you'll still get all the images and text of the website.</li>





</ul>
<p> This approach will let us hit <b><i>effectively 100% of global web traffic with content</i>





</b>





, without changing the workflow of you, the publisher. Own you content. Own your experience. HAX the current market that has forced us all to require they exist in order to have a voice. <a href="https://haxtheweb.org/">HAXTheWeb</a>





.</p>
<p>Here are screenshots of IE6, Safari 4, iPad2, Android 2.2 and Firefox 3 of this site!</p>
<img src="files/safari4.jpg" style="width: 75%;"/><img src="files/ff3.jpg" style="width: 75%;"/><img src="files/android22.jpg" style="width: 25%;"/><img src="files/ipad2.jpg" style="width: 50%;"/><img src="files/ie6.jpg" style="width: 100%;"/> ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Reclaim the web</title>
    <id>https://btopro.com/reclaim-the-web</id>
    <updated>2019-10-16T19:38:54-06:00</updated>
    <published>2019-03-25T08:36:23-06:00</published>
    <summary>Originally from twitter... but this is the power of Dweb methodology and enhanced UX. Previously these thoughts were only ever going to be the property of twitter.Now with HAXcms, I can capture and p</summary>
    <link href="https://btopro.com/reclaim-the-web"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[  ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>HAXcms Theme layer Code Review</title>
    <id>https://btopro.com/haxcms-theme-layer-code-review-2</id>
    <updated>2019-10-16T19:38:54-06:00</updated>
    <published>2019-03-01T13:13:35-07:00</published>
    <summary>Weekly Code ReviewThis 1 starts to get pretty interesting. The team talks about HAXcms, ideates about the new capabilities of the theme layer. This gets into code and great discussion of intentions s</summary>
    <link href="https://btopro.com/haxcms-theme-layer-code-review-2"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <h2 class="hax-active">Weekly Code Review</h2>
<p class="hax-active">This 1 starts to get pretty interesting. The team talks about HAXcms, ideates about the new capabilities of the theme layer. This gets into code and great discussion of intentions surrounding it / needs</p>
<video-player accent-color="light-green" dark="dark" lang="en" preload="metadata" source="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZZIE7oCcM_Q&feature=youtu.be" sticky-corner="top-right" youtube-id="ZZIE7oCcM_Q?feature=youtu.be" iframed="" source-type="youtube" is-a11y-media="" is-youtube="" media-title="HAXcms - Theme layer discussion" style="width: 75%; margin: 0px auto; display: block;"></video-player>
<p>We start getting into what we can add to the theme layer and the JSON object structure we're using could be extended to effectively bring content types and field APIs to HAXcms while keeping life relative to a small JSON format. It's a bit ridiculous how fast this system is.<br/></p>
<p>I talk through the developer theme, slide player, and kick around ideas for what can come next and then <a href="https://twitter.com/hey__mp">@hey__MP</a>

 and <a href="https://twitter.com/cgldevel">@CGLDevel</a>

 show their progress on on a custom theme they're developing for <b><a href="https://haxtheweb.org/">HAXcms</a>

</b>

 which will start to reshape minds about what this is and is possible.<br/></p>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/nikkimk">@NikkiMK</a>

 closes us out by showing how her new rich-text-editor tag is coming along as well as explaining to Chuck (and anyone watching) why we're working on two text editors simultaneously.<br/></p>
<h2>I. Love. This. Team.</h2>
<p>The video closes the way I really feel. I. Love. This. Team.</p>
<p>Keep pushing gang, we're building something amazing that will change the world.</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>ELMS:LN Code review series Part 1</title>
    <id>https://btopro.com/elms-ln-code-review-series-part-1-2</id>
    <updated>2019-10-16T19:38:55-06:00</updated>
    <published>2019-03-01T09:37:33-07:00</published>
    <summary>  Going to get really meta here..  This is a video showing how this blog post was made. The post follows but this video shows the state of HAXcms which is the system being used to develop this </summary>
    <link href="https://btopro.com/elms-ln-code-review-series-part-1-2"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <grid-plate style="width: 100%;" breakpoint-sm="900" breakpoint-md="1200" breakpoint-lg="1500" breakpoint-xl="1800" columns="2" layout="1:1" responsive-size="xs">  <h2 slot="col-1">Going to get really meta here..</h2>






  <p slot="col-1">This is a video showing how this blog post was made. The post follows but this video shows the state of HAXcms which is the system being used to develop this blog and haxtheweb.org and... effectively anything.</p>

<p slot="col-1">The state management in HAXcms is dramatically improved from a few weeks ago and the editing experience in HAXeditor is becoming increasingly more fluid and robust.</p>






  <video-player accent-color="blue" dark="dark" lang="en" preload="metadata" source="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=V8UQOo5d4LQ" sticky-corner="top-right" youtube-id="V8UQOo5d4LQ?undefined" iframed="" source-type="youtube" is-a11y-media="" is-youtube="" media-title="Video showing how this blog post was made" slot="col-2"></video-player>







</grid-plate>
<p><br/></p>
<p>This is to let you all know, that we've got a new "podcast" if you will that will give you a window into our world. Check out <a href="https://github.com/elmsln/hangouts">ELMS:LN hangouts on github</a>








.</p>
<video-player accent-color="teal" lang="en" preload="metadata" source="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o55m5yfdF-o" sticky-corner="top-right" youtube-id="o55m5yfdF-o?undefined" iframed="" source-type="youtube" is-a11y-media="" is-youtube="" media-title="ELMS:LN Code Review - Episode 1" style="width: 75%; margin: 0px auto; display: block;"></video-player>
<p>Here's the <a href="https://github.com/elmsln/hangouts/blob/master/2019/02.11.md">show notes from episode one</a>






:</p>
<md-block source="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/elmsln/hangouts/master/2019/02.11.md" style="width: 100%; margin: 0px auto; display: block;"></md-block>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Fortify</title>
    <id>https://btopro.com/fortify</id>
    <updated>2019-10-16T19:38:54-06:00</updated>
    <published>2019-02-21T21:36:07-07:00</published>
    <summary>"FORT. NIGHT."They yell. Not in the way that teenagers rushing home from school to dominate their friends yell but in the way of innocence. The yell of the joy of dad suggesting that we build a fort</summary>
    <link href="https://btopro.com/fortify"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[  ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Using Webcomponents to unearth the NGDLE</title>
    <id>https://btopro.com/using-webcomponents-to-unearth-the-ngdle</id>
    <updated>2019-09-11T12:13:06-06:00</updated>
    <published>2019-01-29T21:53:20-07:00</published>
    <summary>I find innovation best comes from the cross-sections. The weave between spaces tends to breed the best ideas of the two fabrics to create something new. It is this mentality that's caused me to look o</summary>
    <link href="https://btopro.com/using-webcomponents-to-unearth-the-ngdle"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>I find innovation best comes from the cross-sections. The weave between spaces tends to breed the best ideas of the two fabrics to create something new. It is this mentality that's caused me to look outside the island of edtech first, always asking "What can I bring back to our space to make it better?". 10 years ago, that was Drupal. I evangelized Drupal everywhere I could, wrote hundreds of modules, positively impacted tens of 1000s of sites in and out of education while making it possible for individual developers to leverage open source automation to do awesome things. Today I write to talk about the next thing I want to bring back to our island which I think is <em>the</em>
 technology to bring about an open ecosystem for the Next Generation Digital Learning Environment (NGDLE).</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-webcomponents-explained" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#webcomponents-explained"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Webcomponents explained</h2>
<p>That technology, is webcomponents. Webcomponents, which you can find out more about on <a href="https://www.webcomponents.org/" rel="nofollow">webcomponents.org</a>
 is a four part browser standard that fundamentally changes what's possible in web based application development. The important thing to know is that webcomponents allows developers to define <em>custom HTML elements and expresses how the browser handles them</em>
. So, bringing this back to education: <em>We can use this technology standard in order to build <a href="https://github.com/LRNWebComponents/">pedagogically focused, valid, HTML tags</a>
</em>
.</p>
<h3><a id="user-content-quick-note" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#quick-note"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Quick note</h3>
<p>This is a standard that all major browser vendors have committed to adopting and largely have, though polyfills are required to get full browser support. It also is leaving the IE6/7/8/9/10 world behind (the good news is, <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/technology/microsoft/12087103/Microsoft-to-kill-off-Internet-Explorer-8-9-and-10.html" rel="nofollow">so has Microsoft</a>
).</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-ngdle-backstory" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#ngdle-backstory"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
NGDLE backstory</h2>
<p>For <a href="http://btopro.wordpress.com" rel="nofollow">four years</a>
 I've been building <a href="https://www.elmsln.org/" rel="nofollow">ELMS: Learning Network</a>
; trying to build a platform that can produce and sustain innovation in educational technology. For about that long, Educause has talked about the concept of NGDLE; what it might look like, what it might do, how to do it. Because it's a big concept to unpack, it's taken a few years to get people all on board with the idea and to agree that it's not an LMS (much like webcomponents was proposed in 2011 yet didn't become a real thing implemented until 2016). Because of the patterns of behaviors and methodology of ELMS:LN I currently consider it the only public NGDLE. For that reason, we're misunderstood but if NGDLE is Lego'ing / app-ifying the LMS; ELMS:LN wants to be the grid-plate. The fundamental base-plate to be plugged into. A routing system to stitch it all together and satisfy the need that no vendor will ever provide: a middleware to pull our ecosystems together.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-so-how-do-we-all-lego" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#so-how-do-we-all-lego"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
So how do we all lego</h2>
<p>Ok, so back to webcomponents. If we have a gridplate (you could provide your own, I'm not suggesting ELMS:LN be the only one) then we need lego bricks to plug into the board. But what fits that paradigm? Webcomponents allow you to take simple forms of HTML and build it up into increasingly complex elements. Let's look at a simple concept of a custom tag and how it would start to get towards pedagogically centric HTML.</p>
<p>Just like HTML, custom tags can go into other custom tags. It can also use and retain semantic meaning just like HTML markup. So let's imagine that we had a semantic, custom element that provides the same thing as above. Now we have a tag called <code>paper-button</code>
 and every time I want to do above, I put that tag. Ok, now let's say I want a comment card. A comment card might be:</p>
<p>Which I can then use in something bigger and now I have a tag called <a href="https://lrnwebcomponents.github.io/lrnsys-comment/components/lrnsys-comment/demo/#" rel="nofollow">comment-list</a>
 or <code>discussion-board</code>
. A discussion-board could be made out of any number of other smaller lego brick tags. Now I wire it up to a backend to save the data and I've got a fully functional HTML element that can be shared and remixed anywhere and so long as someone provides a backend to store it, it's going to work.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-critical-concepts-that-webcomponents-provide-to-ngdle-if-we-do-this-right" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#critical-concepts-that-webcomponents-provide-to-ngdle-if-we-do-this-right"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Critical concepts that webcomponents provide to NGDLE if we do this right</h2>
<ol>
<li>Visual consistency - right now when using multiple systems everyone decrys the cognitive load on students. webcomponents can provide a common visual design language and templated approach to help alleviate this. Everything will feel like it's the same (even if it's not)</li>

<li>Accessibility - Because most accessibility mistakes happen when HTML is created, this allows us to make elements with high accessibility baked in, eliminating the ability for end-users to make that design element inaccessible.</li>

<li>Maintainability - If we were to produce a tag such as <code>lrn-assignment</code>
 that expressed an assignment's properties visually, we can now swap out the guts of that tag and so long as the properties going into it are the same we don't need to update any existing content produced.</li>

<li>Interoperability - By design, anything that imports the custom element (which is jsut an HTML file supplying the definition of what to do with that tag) will work. These will work in any system because it's the user's browser that's unpacking what it is and the specification itself gives the element definition and encapsulation.</li>

<li>Standards based approach - by using a common methodology for front-end creation, we can standardize the UX and interaction patterns of our users and allow developers to all work together and utilize each other's lego bricks.</li>

<li>Schema without Schema - We can start to wire up our custom elements to be schematized for indexing by search engines or our own advanced crawlers, ensuring there is additional semantic meaning to our content no matter where it lives. This has <a href="http://oerschema.org" rel="nofollow">huge implications for OER</a>
 for example.</li>

<li>Common Authoring - Because <a href="http://haxtheweb.org" rel="nofollow">we just made this</a>
 and it works anywhere.</li>

</ol>
<h2><a id="user-content-anywhere" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#anywhere"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Anywhere?</h2>
<p>Yeah, anywhere. HAX is another step towards my vision of NGDLE and the solutions we can craft when we work in this approach. An authoring experience that can pull data from anywhere and assemble it in a standards based format (HTML) which can be deployed anywhere. Imagine having identical authoring and instructional capabilities regardless of where an instructor is assembling a course. Open system? Do it in the open. Closed to the institution? Do it in the LMS. Training exercise or learning module on a random blog? Yeah, with an NGDLE based authoring approach, everything can be a mini-LMS and everything can feed other things to make new Learning experiences.
In the coming months through demonstration, documentation and seemingly impossible levels of progress (webcomponents + elmsln make application development trivial) I'll begin to show the path towards anyone building an NGDLE. What it provides users, How we are sharing things across institutions and systems, and how we can start to dissolve all learning systems into the NGDLE based worldview to provide better solutions for instructors and more engaging learning spaces online for learners.</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Creating the decentralized instructional experience app</title>
    <id>https://btopro.com/creating-the-decentralized-instructional-experience-app</id>
    <updated>2019-09-11T12:13:05-06:00</updated>
    <published>2019-01-29T21:53:20-07:00</published>
    <summary>This is based on a submission to the Penn State open innovation challenge for 2018. I like to post my ideas to my blog in addition to my submission so that I never lose them. This one is about the log</summary>
    <link href="https://btopro.com/creating-the-decentralized-instructional-experience-app"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>This is based on a submission to the Penn State open innovation challenge for 2018. I like to post my ideas to my blog in addition to my submission so that I never lose them. This one is about the logical extension to HAX for desktop over 2018 which could be utilized to decentralize instructional experience creation. If this sounds of use to your institution, good, let's work together on it.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-problem" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#problem"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Problem</h2>
<p>Faculty and staff have no idea what they can use at our institution. No matter how many registries of information or solutions we provide, people will need to practically be marketted to just to know they exist in the sea of information about what makes the university work. Beyond this, there is no way to provide continuous innovation to those not at high-touch units which work hand in hand with faculty to produce highly experimental course spaces and approaches. Even if we could find the things we need, very few of them talk to each other, their user experiences are all over the map, and most aren't very good for creating materials without needing to understand technical topics (like HTML). This isn't a PSU specific problem, Duke has an illustration that highlights 93+ solutions available to faculty, many of which don't talk even if they knew them all.
How to solve the problem of finding and once getting there creating engaging experiences?</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-leading-questions" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#leading-questions"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Leading questions</h2>
<ul>
<li>What if faculty and staff involved in producing instructional experiences had an app that told them what services existed and made it instantly possible to use?</li>

<li>What would it look like institutionally and what would the use experience look like?</li>

<li>What needs would we have technically in order to support this?</li>

</ul>
<h2><a id="user-content-vision" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#vision"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Vision</h2>
<p>This is the vision of HAX, a distributed instructional creation tool. <a href="http://haxtheweb.org/" rel="nofollow">HAX can be viewed as a public demo here</a>
. The important thing to keep in mind with this is that desktop publishing of applications can be done using HTML, making them far easier to build when you just make it work on the web. Imagine if users could log into the app on their laptop or phone and just create. Creating a new course? Start one on your local machine and with the press of a button publish it to Canvas, Drupal, ELMS:LN, GravCMS or a static website. Want to see what colleagues have shared from their courses? Fork their materials by searching an institution protected repository right from the app or connect to global shared object repositories. Instead of trying to market to faculty and staff what services are available, have people utilize a unified app which connects to the registry of everything available to them for teaching and learning.
Want to stream video? Upload it to the app and it'll publish it to youtube or the video provider the university supports. Want to create H5P but don't understand hosting? Build it in the app and it'll save to the correct, FERPA valid location. Want to create a slideshow? Drag and drop a series of images which automatically get uploaded to Amazon S3 and then click a UI to "build" your slideshow. Worry about accessibility? HAX will take care of it for you automatically and without the ability to make in-accessible content. Content in HAX is accessible by default due to the game changing technology called <a href="https://www.webcomponents.org/" rel="nofollow">webcomponents</a>
.
Let's get faculty and staff out of the business of understanding HTML and instead build materials that allow them to leverage the services the institution provides without increased cognitive load.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-2018" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#2018"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
2018</h2>
<p>The ELMS:LN team has begun work on such a desktop app called <a href="https://github.com/LRNWebComponents/hax-desktop-app">HAX deskop app</a>
 which seeks to achieve this vision. Help us make this a reality in 2018 and beyond as we seek to empower faculty and align technology deployments with academic freedom and student curiosity.</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>This is not reality</title>
    <id>https://btopro.com/this-is-not-reality</id>
    <updated>2019-09-11T12:13:06-06:00</updated>
    <published>2019-01-29T21:53:20-07:00</published>
    <summary>Chapter 1: The ShowerA Developer takes a shower. A Developer closes his eyes, breathes deeply, and presses the water over his scalp and eyes and face. When hands press against the eye socket in th</summary>
    <link href="https://btopro.com/this-is-not-reality"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <h2><a id="user-content-chapter-1-the-shower" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#chapter-1-the-shower"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Chapter 1: The Shower</h2>
<p>A Developer takes a shower. A Developer closes his eyes, breathes deeply, and presses the water over his scalp and eyes and face. When hands press against the eye socket in the pressense of light, synapese fire off randomly. These random firings of "light" dance in the retina of the Developer seeking the answer to a problem. The retinas of the developer see the sparks trickel away as color fades back in.
The developer pauses.. then does it again, this time focusing on those whips of ocular static fizzle away. The whips form a pattern that looks like a central star that everything is firing out and away, creating their own central stars to fire out and away from. The occular misfires form a fractual image in the minds eye.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-chapter-2-the-fractal" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#chapter-2-the-fractal"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Chapter 2: The fractal</h2>
<p>The developer talks through how a fractal could be used in the design of a system. The developer writes down the fractal. The developer sees a video the next day expressing, visually, the concept of divergent ideas spawning ohter divergent ideas, expressed as a series of hexagons firing off at a tangent and forming new hexagons. The developer recreates the pattern on a whiteboard and begins to theorize how this pattern could be used to represent systems.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-chapter-3-the-monster-within" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#chapter-3-the-monster-within"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Chapter 3: The monster within</h2>
<p>The developer explains this to one other person over two hours. The manager is excited but leaves with: "Who else would ever understand how any of this works though." The developer smiles, "I guess I'll just have to build it to find out". The developer works on prototypes, burning through hundreds of hours beyond what normal projects there are to pursue. The idea is like a dagger in his mind. He starts shutting down from the rest of the world and focusing solely on this one idea. This one fractal.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-chapter-4-the-friend" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#chapter-4-the-friend"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Chapter 4: The friend</h2>
<p>He explains an early prototype to a friend. The friend is intrigued but doesn't get it or see how it's the fractal. The developer keeps pushing on, convinced there is a fractal there. The developer makes prototype after prototype, pouring through hours of tutorials and producing posts and videos looking for someone to understand what he's claiming to have discovered. No one gets it. Again, and again, over the next 2 years, the developer repeats this cycle, trying desperately to get someone to understand the picture in his mind now layed out as code and directory trees. Symlinks and .gitignores. But no one. Gets it.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-chapter-5-the-group" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#chapter-5-the-group"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Chapter 5: The group</h2>
<p>Until... Someone does. Two people actually. And then from two, three, and three, four; and four, five; and five, a dozen, and dozens. Until the fractal no longer is some obscure concept it's the way of visualizing and attacking the problem. The Developer is no longer a developer, and no longer is a young developer either...</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-chapter-6-the-team" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#chapter-6-the-team"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Chapter 6: The team</h2>
<p>The Developer is part of a team. A Team hell bent on innovation. A Team that doesn't accept the world and the educational system the way it is but dreams of what it can be, what it will be. A Team that believes education is not a pidgenholed public service job but the place that fosters and grows innovations of it's own. A Team believes that noone is better then the sun of it's parts.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-chapter-7-the-way-forward" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#chapter-7-the-way-forward"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Chapter 7: The way forward</h2>
<p>A Team of Developers, instructors, instructional designers, designers, students, management; of mixed talents and backgrounds and abilities, form a new fractal pattern within a traditionally stasis laden system.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-chapter-8-the-upside-down" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#chapter-8-the-upside-down"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Chapter 8: The upside down</h2>
<p>The Developer is no longer alone in the wilderness. The Developer is now part of the Team poised to change education, and the world. Join <em>us</em>
.</p>
<iframe src="https://www.elmsln.org/stranger-things/" width="100%" height="500px"></iframe>
<a href="https://www.elmsln.org/stranger-things/">Stranger Things...</a>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Playing for 40</title>
    <id>https://btopro.com/playing-for-40</id>
    <updated>2019-09-11T12:13:06-06:00</updated>
    <published>2019-01-29T21:53:20-07:00</published>
    <summary>A former student employee reached out to me today and, as I've always dreamed of having the experience of a reach teacher, paid me a compliment in the form of successes he now can achieve through impa</summary>
    <link href="https://btopro.com/playing-for-40"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>A former student employee reached out to me today and, as I've always dreamed of having the experience of a reach teacher, paid me a compliment in the form of successes he now can achieve through imparted knowledge.
> ..thank you for teaching me more about being a developer than my degree did
Now, the compliment wasn't meant as a swipe at his education, meerly that "on the job" training was more impactful. As we talked, things came to money and endevours he was undertaking which didn't pay anything currently but gave him something to keep busy.
I've been thinking about writing for awhile and so my response to him (more or less) is what follows. It's less a reponse for him then it is for you, whoever you are. Many, many years ago I went on a rant about getting off the bench and into the game; And the concept keeps coming back to me as I see the view from 2017 looking back on btopro in 2012 when I wrote that. Oh Bryan, if only I could have told you how the next 5 years would play out.
I felt it important in talks, blogging, social media, to always reference that this was my life. That I wasn't going away (at least of my own doing) as a way of trying to solidify my commitments to you, the future of education or those currently engaged in it, that these ideas will not dissipate. I will not bow to the monsters of edtech.
Today, I write to these ends as a means of illustrating the next 5 years. Where I see us going, and how bright the future is.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-dr-jonas-salk" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#dr-jonas-salk"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Dr. Jonas Salk</h2>
<p>So this is written before it's written about me.
</p>
<p>I'm not here for fame.</p>
<p>I'm not here for treasure.</p>
<p>I'm not here for ego.</p>
<p>I'm not here for "work-life balance".</p>
<p>I'm not here for traditional advancement.</p>
<p>I'm here to solve problems using the God given talents and fortunate circumstances I find myself in. I recognition, appreciate, and seek to pursue the fullness of the oppurtunity I have before me. It comes to simple truths.</p>
<p>I <strong>know</strong>
 <em>we</em>
 will change the world. In the last year, ELMS:LN has grown from two people with lines to contributing to the platform to five, internally. Externally there is also a developer at another organization with another one starting soon and <strong>multiple contributions coming from random individuals across the globe</strong>
.</p>
<p>I'm here to be like Dr. Jonas Salk, a hero of mine, who when asked who owned the patent on the cure said:</p>
<p></p>
<h2><a id="user-content-playing-for-40" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#playing-for-40"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
"playing for 40"</h2>
<p>> You see every day, every week and every year of my life I'm always 10 years away from being my hero - <a href="https://youtu.be/wD2cVhC-63I?t=3m11s" rel="nofollow">https://youtu.be/wD2cVhC-63I?t=3m11s</a>

Knowing our history, seeing where we're heading and what is soon to come.. I feel it important to share the phrase I've been focusing on to keep myself grounded. I keep telling people I'm "playing for 40". This is definitely a departure in mindset from me 5 years ago who would claim a stake in the ground for success based on today. No. I'm behaving as if we're only half way there...and I always will.
I love that clip from the video above; I'm always 10 years away from being my hero. Right now, one of my hero's is me at 40. Now, for context, that's 6.5 years away (oi i'm getting old). But it's true. I'm not focusing on today, I'm focusing on where I see us heading in the next 6.5 years as a community and thinking about how we get to that spot.
Right now, ELMS as a project idea is 10 years old. The Learning Network that we breathe is currently ~4 years old. So if we're only 1/2 way to wher I envision us being... what does that look like? Who do we want to be when we grow up?</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-dreaming-reality" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#dreaming-reality"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Dreaming reality</h2>
<p>Feb 18th, 2024:
Get every university on earth to have a level, technical playing field. Ideas should be the drivers of the future, not who's knowledge economy is more built up or financial situation better. Level the technical playing field, start to level other inequalities and disparities in education.
Try to impact every possible learner within or without institutions. Both through formal adoption as well as empowering those with knowledge and information to freely produce, disseminate and mentor with those who are in need of that knowledge.
I believe that through free solutions that work every and anywhere, we can transform education and through transformation of education we can create a better, more perfect society.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-how-do-we-get-there" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#how-do-we-get-there"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
How do we get there?</h2>
<p>Together. It is a small part of a much more complex ecosystem (society), but I believe that by creating the highest quality authoring and learner experiences imaginable and requiring those toolsets be open source that we can do our small part in making that dream a reality.</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>[Alt] + {{reality}}</title>
    <id>https://btopro.com/-alt-reality--1</id>
    <updated>2019-09-11T12:13:06-06:00</updated>
    <published>2019-01-29T21:53:20-07:00</published>
    <summary>Our construction of reality is not the only one. This has always been the case, but I often fall victim to the assumption that because we now have access to more information that we will congeal to a</summary>
    <link href="https://btopro.com/-alt-reality--1"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <video-player lang="en" preload="metadata" source="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bVV2Zk88beY" sticky-corner="top-right" youtube-id="bVV2Zk88beY" iframed source-type="youtube" is-a11y-media is-youtube></video-player>
<p><span style="caret-color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">Our construction of reality is not the only one. This has always been the case, but I often fall victim to the assumption that because we now have access to more information that we will congeal to a singular perspective on subjects. The idea being that more diversity and access to greater world view of people will lead to better opinions.
Unfortunately, this doesn't appear to be the case. Unlike the keystrokes at our disposal and terminal prompts ferrying away command sets with blazing speed and accuracy, the human psyche can't be simple commanded to change.</span><br/></p>
<p class="hax-active">We can't grow up with a set of experiences, form an opinion on a subject, and then have it completely altered effectively in 140 characters. Yet social media and the internet of today, full of drying up "news" rooms and revenue models that favor catching eyeballs as opposed to expanding minds, leads us to dig in harder.
It leads me to two questions: Why do we feel the need to change someone's perspective? And more valuable, how best to go about doing so?</p>
<h3><a id="user-content-why" class="anchor" aria-hidden="" href="#why"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden=""><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>

</svg>

</a>

Why</h3>
<p>Let's start with the easy one: Why? Why must we try and get others to think the way we do when their construction of reality is an alternative fact universe to our own. Part of the human condition is the drive for acceptance. Acceptance by those around us, our group, our circle, whatever you call it, we all want to "fit-in" even when fitting in means associating with the "out" crowd.
So knowing this, how could we possibly expect to get strangers on the internet to agree with our worldview when we have no concept of what their lives actually are? Why do we get consumed by social media and vitriolic arguments simply in the name of our truth being the one real truth (Now where have I heard this argument throughout history let me number the thousands of time periods...).
The Why, is the simplest answer and easier path to achieve to personal satisfaction. It is our primal instinct and hyper-me-centric technology based culture that promotes it. To improve as a society, we must improve as individuals and encourage others to improve as individuals as well. Not by telling why, but by leading others to arrive at our why. Only through honest questioning and engagement can we get others alt-reality to align with our own. When it isn't possible, it's also best to just accept that and move on. There's only a few billion other minds to try and align with anyway.</p>
<h3><a id="user-content-how" class="anchor" aria-hidden="" href="#how"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden=""><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>

</svg>

</a>

How</h3>
<p>So how best to generate the Why in others? The first step is back tracing how we arrived at our own conclusion. How did we become sensative, caring, accepting, loving, charitable, kind, compassionate, whatever the adjective is which is the behaviors we're wishing to exhibit in others. Was it learned through experiences (good or bad)? If so, perhaps it's better to tell a story to try and generate empathy rather then calling someone evil.
How is by far the harder option for engagement, both online and in real life. "I'm depressed" for example can be met with "Why are you depressed?", requiring a level of self-reflection probably not available to the asker (or comes across quazi-confrontational). However, "How can I help you?" is not accusitory or requiring self-reflection, it's walls are down and it's empathizing with the asker.
I wonder how many we could reach with our world view if we treated everyone with an equal level of compassion, regardless of how "evil" their opinion might be. Taking the "How did you come to think that way?" rather than "Why on earth would you ever think that!?" or "Why are you such a monster?"</p>
<h3><a id="user-content-engage" class="anchor" aria-hidden="" href="#engage"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden=""><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>

</svg>

</a>

Engage</h3>
<ul>
<li>When was the last time you deescalated a situation when you were "in the right"? Did it end the conflict or did it burn you more to not win then it was worth?</li>


</ul>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Dood</title>
    <id>https://btopro.com/dood</id>
    <updated>2019-09-11T12:13:06-06:00</updated>
    <published>2019-01-29T21:53:20-07:00</published>
    <summary>dudes crying.dude’s crying.dude, is, crying.This dude, has been crying uncontrollably for the last hour about how wonderful my son is. I'll recall for you what happened and it won't need much mor</summary>
    <link href="https://btopro.com/dood"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>dudes crying.
dude’s crying.
dude, is, crying.
This dude, has been crying uncontrollably for the last hour about how wonderful my son is. I'll recall for you what happened and it won't need much more then that.
We went to a <a href="http://borntobebravetour.com/" rel="nofollow">father son thing about fatherhood and raising sons of integrity</a>
; youth group sorta stuff, a good mix of message, prayer, and fun. The part I wasn't ready for was the label breaking. We had a part where we talked about labels; labels placed on you by others and that you know who you are and you know who God wants you to be and that no one else knows that and can define those labels, those gifts you've been given.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-label" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#label"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Label</h2>
<p>So for this part, your supposed to ask each other what a label people have given you has been (this is admittedly geared toward like 7-15 years old so that's more like teenager question). So I asked him if anyone's said anything mean to him or called him a name at school and he said no (we had very different school experiences apparently already).
So I thought and went, ok, well I'm going to label you Smart and wrote smart on a duct tape (sticker) and placed it on him. Without being asked, he grabbed the pen and wrote on my sticker "Loved" with tears in his eyes he put it on me. I asked why he was crying (afterwards) and he told me "sometimes when people say really nice things about me I feel like... I feel so happy that I start to cry".</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-stars2" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#stars2"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Stars+2</h2>
<p>After this we sat and listened and watched some more. Heard some good stories about integrity (that cheez wiz has none) and how society will tell you that "being a real man" is about money, power, influence, attractiveness, having a wife; and that that's not what's really important. That it's what's on the inside, the person behind the labels and the "things" and the attractiveness that really matters. It was an uplifting message that we all have a role to play and that it's not what you have on the outside but how you live your life that really matters.
We had to leave early because of school early in the morning so we waited for intermission and headed out. The building was on top of a hill overlooking the valley and it was very dark up there outside of the parking lot. As we walked toward the car I scooped him up on my shoulders and instead walked toward a pond in the dark. He wanted to know where we were going and I said he'd see when we got there.
As we got beyond the flood lights of the parking lot I told him to stop and look up. The sky lit up with far more stars then we see at our house.
“woahhhh there’s so many” he said.
"You see those?"
“Yes poppa”
“I love you more then the stars in this sky”
“wow… that’s so nice… I love you more then the stars in the sky… plus 2”
“when I’m older like… 8 and your 54; I’ll still love you cause your the best poppa”
I've been the happiest wreck I've been probably since he was born.</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Generation Uine</title>
    <id>https://btopro.com/generation-uine</id>
    <updated>2019-09-11T12:13:06-06:00</updated>
    <published>2019-01-29T21:53:20-07:00</published>
    <summary>I'd like to put a positive spin on Millennials / Gen Y. As someone who doesn't really feel like he's a Millennial (until reading that most quantify this between 1980 and 2000), I often would read arti</summary>
    <link href="https://btopro.com/generation-uine"/>
    
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[ <p>I'd like to put a positive spin on Millennials / Gen Y. As someone who doesn't really feel like he's a Millennial (until reading that most quantify this between 1980 and 2000), I often would read articles about Gen Y and come to a similar conclusion: Lazy, entitled, bored, unmotivated.
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hER0Qp6QJNU" rel="nofollow">Simon Sinek on Millennials</a>

I enjoy his positive spin on the "Millennial problem", that they (well.. we) find ourself coming into work contexts that we don't believe in. I'd like to expand out of just the positive things about Millennials and what we seek into a single word that I've started to hear to describe my own speaking style.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-how-do-you-get-away-with-that" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#how-do-you-get-away-with-that"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
"How do you get away with that?"</h2>
<p>I've been told since about the 2nd year in the working world (10 years into same career as of this writing) that I can seemingly say anything without retribution. Now obviously this isn't true; but there does seem to be a feeling at times that I'm able to say what people are thinking or address problems directly without emotion or concern for what the consequence.
This may manifest in simple ways such as challenging the status quo or looking at a problem differently then the team is attacking it and not being affraid to say so. At other times this manifests as dropping the F word in meetings to emphasize how much I disagree with a current direction (not angrily, just to emphacize that we need to consider this seriously).
So how is this possible? How do I have so many great friends and enemies (probably way more in this column for those that don't get me). It's because of a single word that I think we desperately lack in the world. It's because I'm <em>Genuine</em>
.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-gen-uine" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#gen-uine"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Gen Uine</h2>
<p>What does Generation Y stand for? Beats me, but I will say that I've noticed we are largely attracted to anything that is genuine. Society is marketing, image management, social studies, over produced vocals, and politicians that run on words like Hope and making things Great; yet still perpetuate the same levels of corruption as previous generations.
We stop going to churches that speak yet don't provide action or community (for refernece I have a church I love and it's because of action and community). We stop watching things that are heavily produced in favor of organic expression online (I'm a cord cutter). We stop paying attention to anything that we don't believe in (I'm not apathetic, I just know what I can/'t influence and focus). We crave genuine discussion and see it avoided in much of the social sphere in favor of arguments from talking points memos fed to mouth pieces for/against whatever the topic (this is why I'm often misidentified as both Liberal and Conservative because I follow logic and truth, not ideological purity).
Be, Genuine. Gen Uine is what I'd much rather be known as then a Millennial or Gen Y or even Bryan Ollendyke or btopro. I don't care if you like me, but I never want you to doubt where I stand on a subject. That's Gen Uine; that's "raw" that's real that's what we desperately lack in society and need to embrace if we're ever to fix the problems we face.
How? Stop worrying about what other people think. Seek out facts, challenge bias. Speak up; for yourself and others. Don't follow the crowd and always question why a group feels the way it does and why you feel that way before joining a group.</p>
<h3><a id="user-content-be" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#be"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Be.</h3>
<p><a href="https://en.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/genuine" rel="nofollow"><em>Gen Uine.</em>
</a>
</p>
 ]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>