<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>bto-pro</title>
    <link></link>
    <description>Mind of the Information Altruist</description>
    <copyright>Copyright (C) 2024 </copyright>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Jan 2024 19:25:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <item>
      <title>The LMS is Cable, We are Roku. Expect Us</title>
      <link>the-lms-is-cable-we-are-roku-expect-us-2</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <h2>Cable</h2>
<p class="highlight"><span class="dropcaps dropcaps-i">I</span>n the 40s and 50s, the Cable industry was born.
By the mid 60s it had almost a million subscribers. In the 70s and 80s the FCC regulated it heavily because of how much of an influence it had on the American consumer. Cable TV was everywhere by the 90s and currently more then 1/2 of all households have cable based TV. It's a massive industry that's dominated by a handful of players. Those players are the brokers of what is allowed to appear on their listings and as channel options expanded, people increasingly felt like there's "nothing on". Still, a majority of people have it because of ease of access (hit the power button on TV and entertainment is there, 0 cognitive load).
Sound familiar? The Cable industry is very similar to the LMS industry. It's been around forever (since early 90s) and has been dominated by only a handful of players in the space. They effectively have a monopoly on the way that educational material is presented and transferred from instructor to learner. They control that pipeline and no matter how many channels (or LTI based apps) you have, everyone still complains there's "nothing on".</p>
<h2>Cord cutting</h2>
<p>While you may have read the term in the news more recently, cord cutting has been a trend since the lat 2000s when Hulu and Netflix began their streaming services, allowing people to go "over the top" so to speak and skip cable while continuing to get information and entertainment. But it really hasn't taken off until recently? If there were options out there, why is it only now getting so much publicity? Hulu and Netflix have been around for about 9 years, why are the currently disrupting cable?</p>
<h2>Enter, the Roku</h2>
<p>Roku is a device that came out 2008 as a device for streaming Netflix and by 2010 starts to support other apps like Hulu and..well.. anyone that wanted on it. You see Roku had an open source SDK that effectively said "if you implement this and notify us, you'll show up in our channel listing". This allowed anyone that had media to stream access to peoples' homes that had a Roku box connected to a TV.
Other reasons Roku was transformative from a user experience perspective:</p>
<ul>
<li>Single box to attach to TV using existing standards (HDMI or RCA)</li>

<li>Approachable input device (simple remote) with Power button activation via TV</li>

<li>No need to understand URLs after initial on-screen directions to setup an account</li>

<li>Icons / images in big bright squares telling you what you are going to access</li>

<li>Start watching / searching within that universe of media
The Roku has transformed the space because it took all those URLs that were always available for Netflix, Hulu, Youtube, Vimeo and the rest, and turned it into something that non-technical people could hook up in 5 minutes. The ease of use and approachability of the technology allowed it to start to decentralize and disrupt the cable industry (which as of this writing is in <a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/espn-losing-subscribers-not-ratings-viewers-2017-9" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">free-fall</a>
)
<h2>The LMS is Cable</h2>

<p>So if the LMS is similar in positioning to Cable, how can we achieve our Roku moment where people decentralized and collapse the usage of the LMS (forcing it to transform how it behaves)? The industry has plenty of "Hulu" and "Netflix" counterparts in the form of systems that start to behave so much like something different that people adopt them in full and they start to look like LMSs of their own. Start with a video quiz tool, add badging, add certification, add a series of trainings, add quizzing, add rosters... HEY! This looks like an LMS (see: <a href="https://darcynorman.net/2013/02/15/normans-law-of-elearning-tool-convergence/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">D’ARCY NORMAN effect</a>
).
So how do we build NGDLE solutions in such a way that they don't just become the next LMS which is trying desperately not to be an LMS, yet is, yet claims it's not... and the cycle repeats.</p>

<h2>NGDLE worldview</h2>

<p>There has to be a way around the current dichotomy of Cable everyone hates and random URLs that have the things people want yet are too hard to use to reach mass adoption; and we're starting to build an attempt at it.
If your familiar with ELMS: Learning Network, a system with lots of individual systems interconnected, then when I say our Roku moment isn't actually ELMS you'll say Waaaaaah?!
Imagine ELMS:LN and it's suite of tools was mostly a backend, administrative functioning system. What if courses, studios, discussions, media and what not were viewed as individual apps on a Roku-esk interface geared towards education. Now, imagine traditional ELMS:LN "apps" are just some of the apps available and we instead showed everything that people could leverage, ELMS and otherwise.</p>

<h2>HAX, Education's Roku moment</h2>

<p>HAX (see other posts here) is short for Headless Authoring eXperience. Imagine though if you weren't just making a webpage though, you were actually constructing a course environment. Then imagine that you did all of this from your laptop, desktop or mobile device. What if a desktop app was your remote control for the construction of <a href="https://btopro.com/blog/creating-the-decentralized-instructional-experience-app" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">educational experiences</a>
. You can call those courses if you like, but the primary focus is on crafting an engaging, high fidelity experience and making it as easy as possible to do.</p>

<h2>HAX's "apps"</h2>

<p>HAX brings to the table two concepts that will provide us with our Roku moment our industry so desperately needs. Sources, and Gizmos (wtf?).</p>

<h3>Sources</h3>

<p>A HAX Source is anything that has or can be given information, media, content, etc. If you are supplying that information, it would look like an upload field:
</p>
<figure class="image"><img alt="Upload field in the Gizmo browser" src="/images/2/a/8/d/7/2a8d74afa5140271b6f0c649a120fa1cf8ab531b-2017-12-2113-42-55.jpeg"/><figcaption>Upload field in the Gizmo browser</figcaption>
</figure>

So you would drag and drop a file to upload, let's say it's a .mp4 file. HAX would ask it's available sources who can handle video. Youtube and Vimeo and anything else would raise their hands. You'd select where you want the video to go and it would start uploading to that source.<p></p>

<h3>Gizmos</h3>

<p>Gizmos (architecturally <a href="https://btopro.com/blog/betting-on-webcomponents-to-bring-about-ngdle" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">webcomponents</a>
) in HAX are your way of presenting information visually. So we either supply media for a source (our .mp4 file) or we search and select one:
</p>
<figure class="image"><img alt="Search sources of information for content" src="/images/f/5/2/8/9/f5289f6ea7389f0fc33fc2881b89d876e253c25f-2017-12-2114-02-25.jpeg"/><figcaption>Search sources of information for content</figcaption>
</figure>

The source says "Hey, I've got something that looks like a video, can any Gizmos handle video". Our Gizmos raise their hand as to who can display video, the user selects the Gizmo for the job:
<figure class="image"><img alt="Gizmo browser to select the right display for the job" src="/images/c/6/6/a/e/c66ae63df2f34fd4a25b1d491f7c55fc29037251-2017-12-2114-02-38.jpeg"/><figcaption>Gizmo browser to select the right display for the job</figcaption>
</figure>

Then they are presented a form for filling in additional details:
<figure class="image"><img alt="Form fields for configuring how to embed this" src="/images/5/4/7/c/8/547c8824829e5067ab1ee347227a5de453c0c596-2017-12-2114-30-55.jpeg"/><figcaption>Form fields for configuring how to embed this</figcaption>
</figure>

After filling out the form, it'll get placed into the content and you can go about doing what you do best. Teach.
<figure class="image"><img alt="Video placed in the page" src="/images/a/c/9/4/b/ac94b93754650a2f42c1af7a0ce307880b5b1c28-2017-12-2114-34-51.jpeg"/><figcaption>Video placed in the page</figcaption>
</figure>
<p></p>

<h3>Desktop app</h3>

<p>Now imagine if <a href="https://github.com/LRNWebComponents/hax-desktop-app" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">HAX were a desktop app</a>
, built using the same methodology as Roku where there are distributed apps that are all pulled together. Because of webcomponents and an awesome desktop builder called Electron, we can pursue both at the same time. We'll be able to improve the distributed building capabilities in ELMS:LN while also putting these capabilities in a desktop publishing app.
The app will then be able to write HTML which can work anywhere, with or without ELMS:LN / other sources, and then also have the ability to deploy to ELMS:LN's course delivery capabilities, or a static location, or a git repo, or any LMS.
By building LMS and system agnostic, we can deploy anywhere. In the coming months you'll start to see the Roku vision rolling out with additional accessibility, usability and integrations available.
The NGDLE will be built out of legos and deployed like Roku.
<a href="https://www.elmsln.org/stranger-things/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">We are ELMS:LN</a>
.
Expect Us.</p>
</li>

</ul>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>item-8cef1ad3-7cc7-778a-b125-1d85f265742d</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 15:29:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using Webcomponents to unearth the NGDLE</title>
      <link>using-webcomponents-to-unearth-the-ngdle-2</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>I find innovation best comes from the cross-sections. The weave between spaces tends to breed the best ideas of the two fabrics to create something new. It is this mentality that's caused me to look outside the island of edtech first, always asking "What can I bring back to our space to make it better?". 10 years ago, that was Drupal. I evangelized Drupal everywhere I could, wrote hundreds of modules, positively impacted tens of 1000s of sites in and out of education while making it possible for individual developers to leverage open source automation to do awesome things. Today I write to talk about the next thing I want to bring back to our island which I think is <em>the</em>
 technology to bring about an open ecosystem for the Next Generation Digital Learning Environment (NGDLE).</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-webcomponents-explained" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#webcomponents-explained"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Webcomponents explained</h2>
<p>That technology, is webcomponents. Webcomponents, which you can find out more about on <a href="https://www.webcomponents.org/" rel="nofollow">webcomponents.org</a>
 is a four part browser standard that fundamentally changes what's possible in web based application development. The important thing to know is that webcomponents allows developers to define <em>custom HTML elements and expresses how the browser handles them</em>
. So, bringing this back to education: <em>We can use this technology standard in order to build <a href="https://github.com/LRNWebComponents/">pedagogically focused, valid, HTML tags</a>
</em>
.</p>
<h3><a id="user-content-quick-note" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#quick-note"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Quick note</h3>
<p>This is a standard that all major browser vendors have committed to adopting and largely have, though polyfills are required to get full browser support. It also is leaving the IE6/7/8/9/10 world behind (the good news is, <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/technology/microsoft/12087103/Microsoft-to-kill-off-Internet-Explorer-8-9-and-10.html" rel="nofollow">so has Microsoft</a>
).</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-ngdle-backstory" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#ngdle-backstory"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
NGDLE backstory</h2>
<p>For <a href="http://btopro.wordpress.com" rel="nofollow">four years</a>
 I've been building <a href="https://www.elmsln.org/" rel="nofollow">ELMS: Learning Network</a>
; trying to build a platform that can produce and sustain innovation in educational technology. For about that long, Educause has talked about the concept of NGDLE; what it might look like, what it might do, how to do it. Because it's a big concept to unpack, it's taken a few years to get people all on board with the idea and to agree that it's not an LMS (much like webcomponents was proposed in 2011 yet didn't become a real thing implemented until 2016). Because of the patterns of behaviors and methodology of ELMS:LN I currently consider it the only public NGDLE. For that reason, we're misunderstood but if NGDLE is Lego'ing / app-ifying the LMS; ELMS:LN wants to be the grid-plate. The fundamental base-plate to be plugged into. A routing system to stitch it all together and satisfy the need that no vendor will ever provide: a middleware to pull our ecosystems together.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-so-how-do-we-all-lego" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#so-how-do-we-all-lego"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
So how do we all lego</h2>
<p>Ok, so back to webcomponents. If we have a gridplate (you could provide your own, I'm not suggesting ELMS:LN be the only one) then we need lego bricks to plug into the board. But what fits that paradigm? Webcomponents allow you to take simple forms of HTML and build it up into increasingly complex elements. Let's look at a simple concept of a custom tag and how it would start to get towards pedagogically centric HTML.</p>
<p>Just like HTML, custom tags can go into other custom tags. It can also use and retain semantic meaning just like HTML markup. So let's imagine that we had a semantic, custom element that provides the same thing as above. Now we have a tag called <code>paper-button</code>
 and every time I want to do above, I put that tag. Ok, now let's say I want a comment card. A comment card might be:</p>
<p>Which I can then use in something bigger and now I have a tag called <a href="https://lrnwebcomponents.github.io/lrnsys-comment/components/lrnsys-comment/demo/#" rel="nofollow">comment-list</a>
 or <code>discussion-board</code>
. A discussion-board could be made out of any number of other smaller lego brick tags. Now I wire it up to a backend to save the data and I've got a fully functional HTML element that can be shared and remixed anywhere and so long as someone provides a backend to store it, it's going to work.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-critical-concepts-that-webcomponents-provide-to-ngdle-if-we-do-this-right" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#critical-concepts-that-webcomponents-provide-to-ngdle-if-we-do-this-right"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Critical concepts that webcomponents provide to NGDLE if we do this right</h2>
<ol>
<li>Visual consistency - right now when using multiple systems everyone decrys the cognitive load on students. webcomponents can provide a common visual design language and templated approach to help alleviate this. Everything will feel like it's the same (even if it's not)</li>

<li>Accessibility - Because most accessibility mistakes happen when HTML is created, this allows us to make elements with high accessibility baked in, eliminating the ability for end-users to make that design element inaccessible.</li>

<li>Maintainability - If we were to produce a tag such as <code>lrn-assignment</code>
 that expressed an assignment's properties visually, we can now swap out the guts of that tag and so long as the properties going into it are the same we don't need to update any existing content produced.</li>

<li>Interoperability - By design, anything that imports the custom element (which is jsut an HTML file supplying the definition of what to do with that tag) will work. These will work in any system because it's the user's browser that's unpacking what it is and the specification itself gives the element definition and encapsulation.</li>

<li>Standards based approach - by using a common methodology for front-end creation, we can standardize the UX and interaction patterns of our users and allow developers to all work together and utilize each other's lego bricks.</li>

<li>Schema without Schema - We can start to wire up our custom elements to be schematized for indexing by search engines or our own advanced crawlers, ensuring there is additional semantic meaning to our content no matter where it lives. This has <a href="http://oerschema.org" rel="nofollow">huge implications for OER</a>
 for example.</li>

<li>Common Authoring - Because <a href="http://haxtheweb.org" rel="nofollow">we just made this</a>
 and it works anywhere.</li>

</ol>
<h2><a id="user-content-anywhere" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#anywhere"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Anywhere?</h2>
<p>Yeah, anywhere. HAX is another step towards my vision of NGDLE and the solutions we can craft when we work in this approach. An authoring experience that can pull data from anywhere and assemble it in a standards based format (HTML) which can be deployed anywhere. Imagine having identical authoring and instructional capabilities regardless of where an instructor is assembling a course. Open system? Do it in the open. Closed to the institution? Do it in the LMS. Training exercise or learning module on a random blog? Yeah, with an NGDLE based authoring approach, everything can be a mini-LMS and everything can feed other things to make new Learning experiences.
In the coming months through demonstration, documentation and seemingly impossible levels of progress (webcomponents + elmsln make application development trivial) I'll begin to show the path towards anyone building an NGDLE. What it provides users, How we are sharing things across institutions and systems, and how we can start to dissolve all learning systems into the NGDLE based worldview to provide better solutions for instructors and more engaging learning spaces online for learners.</p>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>item-1222b362-d24d-0aa7-20e7-724767f57656</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 15:29:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Innovation's four ingredients</title>
      <link>innovation-s-four-ingredients-2</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p class="highlight"><span class="dropcaps dropcaps-i">I</span> saw this picture at Disney's Test Track ride and had to take a picture. I love that the build up to this ride they have lots of (propaganda) pictures, prototypes and interviews with people about cars. What cars mean to them, what they represent in American culture, what they're experiences were with cars and why these designers got passionate about creating designs for new cars.</p>
<p>While this is what Disney does to pass the time while waiting in a multiple hour line, this one stood out to me because while a Chevy commercial from start to finish, it was at least a cool and inspiring Chevy commercial. These four words had little descriptive signs to go with them early on in the ride (aka start of the line) which talked about the components to any new car or idea that they would come up with. I like these four concepts for building something new and wanted to bring them to our edTech world we build.</p>
<h2>Line</h2>
<p>Designers start with an idea.  We get an idea from anywhere, maybe something we saw we liked or something we're reacting to that we didn't. No matter what the idea though it starts with jotting it down. Taking notes, reflecting (with lots of coffee and music) about what we could build. Writing and drawing are the first phase to bringing something new into existence.</p>
<h2>Clay</h2>
<p>Then it's time to prototype the idea. We have to take it from sketches and, again with lots of coffee and music, bring that idea to reality on a screen. Maybe it's not the finished product, but it's enough of a sculpting of future reality that we can bring our vision to life in the eyes of someone attune to what we are expressing. The clay phase isn't finalized but it at least is semi-functional and allows us to get confirmation (or rejection) of the premise we're building against so that we can form it more fully later.</p>
<h2>Math</h2>
<p>Next after refinement as a block of clay it's time to take the idea and ensure it fits with the laws of physics. In edTech, our "laws of physics" is often constraints of delivering media on the web. Package size, dependencies on other existing things, extending our universe of tools to be as robust as possible without bloating it. Beyond this, our laws extend into actual laws like needing to account for accessibility and universal design.</p>
<h2>Emotion</h2>
<p>Passion for the car and what your building. We certainly align here and this word was really what lead me to want to write it down. If you don't have passion for what you're building, then you need to find some place that does bring you that satisfaction in life. We bring an undying passion to our work, knowing the creations we build are used to impact the minds of thousands. It's not easy designing future systems, especially not politically, but keeping in mind who we're here to serve makes it all worth it.</p>
<p>You can see emotion in what I write, I'm told it's visible in what I say in presentations too (though that's usually the coffee + coffee + music doing that). I've been told lately it's infectious and that's really good to hear; cause several years ago @btopro wasn't as well received or appreciated for enthusiasm.  When your outside the <a innertext="Overton window" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Overton_window" title="Overton window political theory" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">Overton window</a>

, people will reject what your saying. If you really do believe in what you're preaching, then it's on you not to try and change them (or you) but to change the way you message what you believe.</p>
<p>Simple language changes can trigger a reaction of "wow I see it that way now" instead of "what are you pushing now?". Don't give up. Organizations want to remain at rest unless acted upon by an unstoppable force. Be that force of change in whatever you aspire to do.</p>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>item-6c53744c-1b33-97a1-976f-90484f5bc450</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 15:29:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Straddling the Abyss</title>
      <link>straddling-the-abyss-2</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <h2>The tight rope walker</h2>
<p class="highlight"><span class="dropcaps dropcaps-h">H</span>e looks to his left..</p>
<p>certain death.He tilts to the right, also, certain death. It would appear that the only path forward, was the only way to go. No ability to step backward, only to move forward step by step. Step too far one way and risk having to over correct. Over correct too far and the entire thing comes to a stand still at best; at worst, the journey is over.</p>
<p>I got to talk to my wife the other night before bed. It's intended as it sounds; rare lately. 2018 has been very busy for us. Lots of travel, lots of juggling schedules of kids, jobs, extra work on both our parts, and so as any parents of two young children know the conversation time without the noise of life is often rare. It was in this moment that I used a phrase I haven't fully explained previously.</p>
<p>It was that of where my work is heading and the creeping abyss that I see myself needing to avoid. She asked what I meant by having to approach the abyss (in reference to our work and where it's going). I'm not really one to bring conversations that are really personal in matter up in a public form but if none speak that which is abnormal then all that remains is what others claim as normalcy.</p>
<h2>Everyone is miserable at the top</h2>
<p>So how can we get to the top without becoming miserable in the process or losing our soul? I have yet to meet anyone or hear of anyone (but one person) who has done the whole parable of the fisher thing and not ended up the same as they left off. The parable is a man is fishing by a lake and someone says "wow you're really good at this, you should form a company and sell these fish to others". And so he either relates the following or lives it but basically it goes that if you stop doing what you love just because you love it and turn it into a financial enterprise, you had better make sure you never lose sight of that love or you'll risk it just becoming another job. A job the fisherman wants to ultimately escape and go back to sitting by the lake and fishing alone.</p>
<p>Without having to detail who these people are (nor should I) I can sadly tell you that most people I've met that run open source projects that have taken off are often broken people. Maybe I just know the wrong ones, but so many fall to the social ills that plague us all yet are even easier to come by when money and "power" come into play. Drugs, sex, broken homes, distance from family and friends, unfulfillment in the life's work they have selected. If these weren't common problems in our space you wouldn't see so many conference talks about topics of Burn out, imposter syndrome and generally being a person outside of tech.</p>
<p>This, is the abyss. Fame. Vanity. The whole lot of the typical "7 deadly sins" as it were. This is the abyss that from day one I've recognized and made sure never to cross over. It doesn't mean I don't have fun at events, it doesn't mean I don't have friends in the communities I partake. But it does mean that I'm always in control of myself and any situation I'm a part of. I can't let go, and I won't; even if it seems I'm there in my mind I've carved out a safe place to hide.</p>
<p>Never get so deep into your work that you forget why you were doing the work in the first place. Never proceed through life without purpose, vision, intention, desire, love, hope or dreams. Find your why, embrace it and never let go. It seems silly, but finding your Why, having guiding principles and living them are what separate a fulfilling life from an empty one. It's all mindset, and prioritizing things to ensure you achieve what you've set out to do.</p>
<h2>Why then...</h2>
<p>My parents told me only more recently, that part of their desire to do the best in life they could was to provide a better existance for me and my sisters. It resonated immediately... as my early presentations when I'd launch into what I was doing always started with Why I was doing it (followed by silly pictures of my kids). My Why's are simple, solid, and core to my being</p>
<p>Because my (and your) children deserve a better world then the already pretty awesome one I was given</p>
<p>Because we can always do better</p>
<p>Because education raises all ships and allows us to bring greater understanding and joy to this world as a result</p>
<p>Because money isn't everything</p>
<p>Because with great power, comes great responsibility.</p>
<p>Because this is my calling.</p>
<h2>Always have something to look up to, something to chase, and a hero</h2>
<video-player resource="#567e6b42-4a22-c7ad-4f65" prefix="oer:http://oerschema.org/ schema:http://schema.org/ dc:http://purl.org/dc/terms/ foaf:http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/ cc:http://creativecommons.org/ns# bib:http://bib.schema.org " responsive="" text-color-class="white-text" text-color="#ffffff" video-style="style1" style="width: 100%;" source="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wD2cVhC-63I" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/wD2cVhC-63I?showinfo=0&controls=1&rel=0" iframed="" width="560" height="315" caption="Matthew McConaughey, Oscar® acceptance speech 2014." secondary-color="#ff6f00" secondary-color-class="amber darken-4" yt-nocookie="" yt-controls="" video-color="ull" class="x-scope video-player-0" sticky-corner="top-right" dark="">
</video-player>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>item-401610da-127f-602f-5298-265f5eea00ee</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 15:29:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Knowledge Decentralization Manifesto</title>
      <link>the-knowledge-decentralization-manifesto-2</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p class="highlight"><span class="dropcaps dropcaps-a">A</span>ccess to knowledge is a control system.</p>
<p>As the "<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Forbidden_fruit" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">Apple of Eden</a>
" unlocked the power to question so too is the case with all modern knowledge transfer technologies. Knowledge corrupts established thought, expands horizons, and changes human outcomes in powerful ways. It has network effects of its own and so, it is imperative that we as producers and orchestrators of knowledge production, management and dissemination acknowledge the power we wield. We have the power to shape society. So how best can we utilize our talents to maximize empowerment?</p>
<p><em>It is an ethical imperative that we seek the fundamental transformation of higher education to maximize quality and access to knowledge</em>
. This transformation will empower the globe to increase empathy, maximize personal freedom and personal growth through increased educational equality.</p>
<h2>Change knowledge dissemination; change everything.</h2>
<p>We will build a more open, more accessible, more equal opportunities, and as a result a more just society through the empowerment of all regardless of background, experience, status or financial means. What structural problems must we attack in order to fundamentally alter the dissemination and production of knowledge? What philosophy of system design can we adopt in order to change structural inequality?</p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Actor–network_theory" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">Actor network theory</a>
 offers a critical lens with which to view production and implementation of knowledge dissemination technologies. TLDR; all machines and human connections influence one another equally and their relative positioning to one another is important. Simply using a tool is not enough, the tool must provide affordances that eliminate structural inequality in knowledge production and dissemination.</p>
<p>To illustrate that there is a difference in possibilities through knowledge dissemination usage</p>
<figure class="image"><figcaption>A, B contrasting knowledge dissemination and learning environment management</figcaption>
</figure>
<p>All knowledge is produced by accessing website X. All knowledge seekers access website X.
A counter to this approach is similar in initial access but maximizes flexibility and potential quality of experience
All knowledge is produced in any location that best meets its needs (Solution Y), then referenced in website X. All knowledge seekers access website X, but are pushed out to website Y.</p>
<h2>Decentralization of knowledge construction</h2>
<p>This decentralization of knowledge construction still affords the minimal amount of centralization required to avoid chaos, which I shall deem <a href="https://btopro.wordpress.com/2011/03/21/structured-anarchy/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">structured anarchy</a>
. The point of decentralizing knowledge production is not to produce chaos, it is to provide more vibrant, local options to better meet the needs of knowledge producers based on the topic of choice. We don't setup science lab classes expecting to teach forestry in them. We don't expect our doctors of tomorrow to learn while dangling from a tree harness.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Why then should it be absurd to construct technology environments that best meet the needs of the topic at hand?</p>

</blockquote>
<p>Seeding this ground, that all learning environments and knowledge production silos are the same, forces us to accept structural failings of today's learning management systems which better resemble a theocracy then today's vibrant internet culture. These structural failures lead to simple technical ones that are difficult for modern knowledge produces to understand (yet are forced to accept)</p>
<figure class="image"><img alt="A typical cycle produced by lack of empowerment" src="/images/a/8/3/1/f/a831fce14cbe3278c7b745d4be271d51101052b4-the-last-30-years-of-knowledge-dissemination.jpeg"/><figcaption>A typical cycle produced by lack of empowerment</figcaption>
</figure>
<ul>
<li>Want to improve engagement with learners and knowledge seekers? No, the theocracy doesn't allow JavaScript.</li>

<li>Want to improve perception of knowledge quality through design? No, the theocracy demands understanding of complex technical underpinnings.</li>

<li>Want to reference or pull in external knowledge? Yes, but only if it follows our ridged, dated orthodoxies of API design.</li>

</ul>
<h2>There's another way out.</h2>
<p>A phrase has emerged (circa 2014) to attempt to encompass the antithesis of the theocratic knowledge production market. <a href="https://library.educause.edu/resources/2014/9/next-generation-digital-learning-environment-initiative" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">Next Generation Digital Learning Environments (NGDLE)</a>
 is thought of as the response to legacy theocratic knowledge dissemination technologies. NGDLE embraces knowledge construction by leveraging a free and open internet as well as the construction of new learning ecosystems. It seeks maximal freedom for knowledge producers to utilize whatever methods of production they can access in order to best disseminate knowledge to those seeking it.</p>
<p>The theocratic knowledge production market has attempted to utilize existing methods of structural inequality in order to perpetuate their control in the name of next generation. It utilizes legacy standards like Learning Tools Interoperability (LTI) in order to claim that it has embraced the internet by providing a window out to it.</p>
<p></p>
<figure class="image"><img alt="Visualizing LTI Entrapment" src="/images/4/f/8/e/d/4f8ede8b429c64be36876f9e5103415bcc806f7a-lti-entrapment.jpeg"/><figcaption>Visualizing LTI Entrapment</figcaption>
</figure>
<p></p>
<p>"Look at us, we've changed. No really, we have. We <em>allow you</em>
 to access (some) additional methods of construction. Just stay with us, please, we've changed." the theocratic knowledge production market says. Like an abusive lover though, it hasn't actually changed, it's just gotten a haircut and bought flowers (or, you know, adopted Twitter's bootstrap framework and claimed the high ground of usability as a result).</p>
<p></p>
<figure class="image"><img alt="Theocratic knowledge production market where it really is, where it claims, and then where NGDLE and my projects attempt to take society" src="/images/7/f/3/0/0/7f300005440f74a78d82542a2e3c3f0bb56dd8c2-innovation-in-course-infrastructure.jpeg"/><figcaption>Theocratic knowledge production market where it really is, where it claims, and then where NGDLE and my projects attempt to take society</figcaption>
</figure>
<p></p>
<p>The knowledge production theocracy wants you; needs you; no, demands that you stay in a stasis.</p>
<h2>But you don’t need them</h2>
<p>NGDLE is not about building up a long dead, one sided relationship (and ideology). It's an approach that says we need to tell the LMS that "we're cool, we've moved on. We can still be friends though". I mean, LMS still has all your CDs in its car and you can't just leave 40 or 50 CDs in LMS's car right? No, don't abandon your CDs in LMS's car; I'm saying though that we need to consider how we can make LMS useful the best self it can be too. The LMS was never meant to do too much, but we previously demanded that it do so. Like every Disney villain, they aren't purely evil, the theocratic knowledge production market is just misguided. It's going where capitalism has allowed it to go and needs a purely decentralized, internet mindset in order to right the (sinking) ship.</p>
<p>NGDLE more than technology construction is about aligning the foundational principle of academic freedom with technology freedom. While the theocratic knowledge production market provides and enforces bland experience construction; NGDLE by contrast fosters personal growth, seeking new idea and expanding horizons through the intentional decentralization of knowledge production and dissemination.</p>
<p></p>
<figure class="image"><img alt="A network of solutions across the wider internet" src="/images/e/2/a/e/8/e2ae8d1aa89d07c58512dca2372ab8dcc6ddfa9b-knowledge-producer.jpeg"/><figcaption>A network of solutions across the wider internet</figcaption>
</figure>
<p></p>
<p>This is why NGDLE has been so difficult for anyone to embrace (or build for that matter...ELMS:LN is 4 years old and only now is making sense in discussions I have or slides). NGDLE is not a product. It is a mindset, a method of knowledge assembly that ensures no centralized authority can exist. Without centralization, it's very difficult for the theocratic knowledge production market (as it presently exists) to make money. And if it's purely profit driven (spoiler alert: they don't care about you no matter how big their conference, they want your money).</p>
<h2>Bringing the market to succumb to NGDLE</h2>
<p>If the market existed, then capitalism alone would provide it right? We've been asking for these products and the theocratic knowledge production market provided. To which I'd retort... when Toys R Us existed and we all went to a centralized location to buy toys, did we sit around and think "huh, there's gotta be a way we can get rid of this process and provide better outcomes". I mean, the market produced a solution to a need, we utilized it, so it was clearly the best (I mean they had a run for 70+ years<span style="font-size: 1em;">).</span></p>
<p>Some will argue the market caught up with them (Amazon specifically) but what really happened? Amazon embraced a decentralized access methodology, aka internet centric access and development method. By increasing pressure in the server and supply chain automation space they were able to collapse the theocratic toy purchase market.</p>
<h2>Forces to support which will decentralize the theocratic knowledge production market</h2>
<p>Support these efforts, and we collectively can disrupt the theocratic knowledge production market</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://paulhibbitts.net/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">Paul Hibbits Course Hub GravCMS project</a>
</li>

<li><a href="https://reclaimhosting.com/domain-of-ones-own/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">Reclaim hosting - Domain of One's Own</a>
</li>

<li><a href="https://www.tsugi.org/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">Tsugi</a>
</li>

</ul>
<p>Stand up for voices that are attacking the theocratic knowledge production market and are using their money and their feet to demonstrate their commitment to ending it. Paul's work illustrates the power of the individual to get up and leave and not fail. Reclaim hosting is an example of how an edge industry and further erode confidence in the theocratic knowledge production market. Tsugi is a representation of how we can micro service the theocratic knowledge production market into a position where you start questioning why you have an LMS. I will say that as I'm far more aggressive in my NGDLE stance then Dr. Chuck, his technology embraces the theocratic knowledge production market too much and will ensure that it always exists.</p>
<p>I am a hardline NGDLE believer. I am change. I am a <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Tempered-Radicals-People-Difference-Inspire/dp/0875849059" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">Tempored Radical</a>
. As a result, the fronts that I push on and will continue to push on are far more decentralized then these approaches. All three of the above empower people... to continue to use the theocratic knowledge production market over the long term. They build up their users for sure, but in any social declaration of where we can go, someone needs to try and be the goal post.</p>
<h2>Story of the arbiters of the digital revolution</h2>
<p></p>
<figure class="image"><img alt="Story of the arbiters of the digital revolution - Ex Uno Plura" src="/images/2/5/c/3/6/25c3621ff811cd108abb40b63a8bdf6544439ce3-20180316163855.jpeg"/><figcaption>Story of the arbiters of the digital revolution - Ex Uno Plura</figcaption>
</figure>
<p></p>
<p>These represent my own efforts to bring about the decentralization of knowledge production in order to Transform Education.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="http://haxtheweb.org/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">#HAXtheweb</a>
 - Decentralized, OER Schema aware knowledge construction platform. Run an identical authoring experience regardless of platform and leverage the web as a whole. Work on a desktop, a phone, locally, in a CMS, in an LMS? Doesn't matter. HAX is intended to be a decentralized production system which makes writing complex HTML trivial. It's also engineered to allow developers to extend the authoring experience by simply extending the web (through web component based architecture, ala LRN Web components below).</li>

<li><a href="https://www.elmsln.org/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">ELMS:LN</a>
 - ELMS: Learning Network - A system of systems, built with NGDLE in mind. It is engineered to power HAX (and HAX power it). It provides methods for environment construction so that educators can have more vibrant learning ecosystems rather then single widget-y + 1 tools. ELMS:LN pulls all of these technologies and grows in capabilities as elements make it possible. It is both experiment and development platform for testing new pedagogical idea as they relate to design as well as delivering higher quality experiences then traditional LMS can produce.</li>

<li><a href="https://www.webcomponents.org/author/LRNWebComponents" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">LRN Web components</a>
 - LRN Web Components is an ever expanding design and functionality component set that powers ELMS:LN, HAX and any system that we develop. It allows for an insane amount of reuse across educational projects and is intended to solve the NGDLE problem of cognitive load on learners via design and development consistency making environments easier to use and develop.</li>

<li><a href="http://oerschema.org/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">OER Schema</a>
 - Schema for expressing pedagogy. It extends Schema.org and provides semantic meaning to all of the elements produced as part of LRN Web Components, meaning that every system (edtech or otherwise) that implement LRN Web Components will be getting wired for OER Schema. This will provide a more vibrant search and remix experience for OER content produced over the long haul of society.</li>

</ul>
<p></p>
<figure class="image"><img alt="UX Normalization visual relative to LRN / HAX" src="/images/d/d/0/e/7/dd0e7f557617ee84a120654dd614beb5296a1d9d-ux-normalization.jpeg"/><figcaption>UX Normalization visual relative to LRN / HAX</figcaption>
</figure>
<p></p>
<p></p>
<figure class="image"><img alt="Example of two different courses leveraging similar UX conventions" src="/images/d/7/9/c/2/d79c26a98c1ee2637e938567a3caacb904fa2d16-2-courses.jpeg"/><figcaption>Example of two different courses leveraging similar UX conventions</figcaption>
</figure>
<p></p>
<h2>I'll see you in the future.</h2>
<p>We can develop in minutes what takes the establishment months to envision. When we give these technologies away. When we work with faculty person to person to empower them not to stand on our shoulders but to stand on their own, completely independent of us (via HAX). There is no limit to what we can do when we start working together.</p>
<p>I will be told that I'm full of myself, and often have, and that's fine. But if Hawkings felt he couldn't be better than Einstein he never would have tried. If it wasn't an active journey to be the best, to liberate the most, . I can pledge to you now, whoever you are, that you have a critical role to play in the future development of educational technology solutions and helping improve structural inequality, if you want to.</p>
<p>I'm standing up, and I won't back down from these ideas, technologies, and approaches. My heroes are probably a little different than yours. My heroes are people like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jonas_Salk" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">Jonas Salk</a>
, inventor of the Polio vaccine that refused to patton it. Like <a href="http://www.dr-chuck.com/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">Dr. Charles R. Severance</a>
 who's crazy enough to believe in a communication's protocol so deeply that he'd get tattoos of those that implemented it (as an LTI founder and me viewing LTI as evil, we're a fun party pack). Like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Stallman" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">Richard Stallman</a>
 who is unapologetic in his adherence to open source and free software. And all those that donate their time and efforts in order to empower others to build solutions for themselves.</p>
<p>I've passed up money, promotions, companies, consulting, time with loved ones (the big picture is a better future for my boys); because of an idea which I know to be true: any individual can change the world. I will change whatever educational equity issue I can resolve in my life time, or will at least work as hard as I can towards attempting to resolve those issues. I've been blessed with an amazing opportunity in this world... to write code that I can release in hopes of making an impact. I know that if you'd join us and do the same, that we can improve access, increase quality, and eliminate the need for anyone to be dependent on anyone else to disseminate knowledge.</p>
<p>Will you join me in trying to be more than just a vapor in this world but to leave a legacy as the people that stood up and caused a social movement that saw a dramatic improvement in education and knowledge production systems? Through better solutions, people will be able to better empathize with one another, have a bigger world view, and reduce real world conflicts. Through better solutions we'll get knowledge out to people in faraway places and disadvantaged nearby ones that build people up and teach them how to fish on their own. That give them untold experiences without the need to take on hundreds of thousands of dollars of debt.</p>
<p>Ex Uno Plura - Out of one, many. Be that one that can bring forth the empowerment of many.</p>
<p><em>Bryan Todd Ollendyke</em>
</p>
<p><em>March 16th, 2018.</em>
</p>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>item-f82147b6-1844-d3c0-9515-01130ce85c79</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 15:29:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Knowledge Decentralization Manifesto (The Prolog)</title>
      <link>the-knowledge-decentralization-manifesto-the-prolog-2</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p></p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>item-c150b20f-d7ed-4a1d-1ca5-7b4406c040a9</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 15:29:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HAX apereo piece</title>
      <link>hax-apereo-piece-2</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>Once you see HAX, and realize how it works, you won't be able to unsee it. What is HAX? HAX is short for Headless Authoring eXperience; meaning that we've decoupled the authoring of content and media from any backend storage system. This frees us to build the best authoring solution for the web. Not specifically for ELMS:LN, or Sakai, or Tsugi but for the web in general. HAX does this through a front-end technology called web components. Web components have been in the pipeline of the web for many years, but the time is finally right to start jumping on board and planning for how to use them in the future. Web components in short are a four part specification already in most browsers fully (or polyfill-ed in) which allows for the creation of new, custom html tags that the browser recognizes. This nets you modular / component driven development without the need for bloated frameworks like Angular, React, etc. HAX leverages this technology to build a form of web components authoring web components. This means that we can build new custom elements that any browser understands, and have it fire up a single JSON object and IF hax is around it will understand how to build a UI for it. HAX based content will never appear to have been made with HAX, because it's just writing data into web component properties the same way any developer could. This means faculty can start authoring advanced HTML without ever looking at it. It also means we as developers can build and expand our systems using open standards without frameworks limiting who can plug and play where. The #usetheplatform movement is lively and is ultimately the replacement for all frameworks or at least huge chunks of them while allowing us to share visual and functional assets. Interested in helping us #haxtheweb? Check out some links: * [http://haxtheweb.org](http://haxtheweb.org) - this is a demo which is completely headless * [https://github.com/LRNWebComponents](https://github.com/LRNWebComponents) - our open element library, currently north of 130 elements that work anywhere * [https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLJQupiji7J5eTqv8JFiW8SZpSeKouZACH](https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLJQupiji7J5eTqv8JFiW8SZpSeKouZACH) - #haxtheweb playlist of tutorials, demonstrations, and ramblings This is an effort that can benefit any Apereo project and the ELMS:LN core team would happily entertain collaborations to help bring HAX to more than just ELMS:LN's community. Currently there are HAX integrations for Drupal (6,7), BackdropCMS, GravCMS and ELMS:LN. HAX is slated to be the default authoring experience for ELMS:LN by Fall 2018 with pilot to real people happening Summer 2018. *[this piece was originally written for the Apereo newsletter](https://www.apereo.org/)</p>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>item-79649f12-a6d2-98f5-3c0b-8b88f2a24457</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 15:29:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The perfect cup of coffee</title>
      <link>the-perfect-cup-of-coffee-2</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>(post via <a href="https://twitter.com/btopro" rel="nofollow">@btopro on twitter</a>
)</p>
<p>good people of the internet who drink coffee. I am about to embark on a delicious journey. A journey of mind altering chemicals pour perfectly at home. A journey, into <a href="https://twitter.com/DeathWishCoffee" rel="nofollow">@DeathWishCoffee</a>
</p>
<p>I remember as a child, and seeing the tools of my father or grandfather's workshop and thinking "wow... how did they amass all those tools" and they'd tell me "one at a time son. One at a time" (this is not my reality this was stolen from Gran Torino). Today. I have my toolshed</p>
<p>The difference, is my toolshed is stocked with what assembles the perfect cup of coffee. Let me tell you, how to experience the perfect cup of Saturday afternoon coffee (I should NOT be drinking this this late in the day I'll be up for days).</p>
<p>First. A gallon bottle of distilled water and a packet of <a href="https://twitter.com/thirdwavewater" rel="nofollow">@thirdwavewater</a>
 . Mix the two. Then get clear 20 oz coffee cup and fill it with the water almost to the top. Now get a <a href="https://twitter.com/BonavitaWorld" rel="nofollow">@BonavitaWorld</a>
 tea kettle with a digital readout and pour the water into it. Add 1 oz for steam loss</p>
<p>Next take out an <a href="https://twitter.com/aeropresscom" rel="nofollow">@aeropresscom</a>
 coffee maker and <a href="https://twitter.com/DeathWishCoffee" rel="nofollow">@DeathWishCoffee</a>
 . Put 5 scoops (small scooper) of death wish into a grinder of your choice (I have a 14$ proctorsillex by <a href="https://twitter.com/HamiltonBeach" rel="nofollow">@HamiltonBeach</a>
). Pulse grinder till beans are just above expresso level grinded.</p>
<p>Start the Bonavita set at 195 degrees and select the hold setting. You want 195 not 195 then cool off to 193 or some other garbage temperature. Using the inverted pour method (<a href="http://coffeenate.com/how-to-make-coffee-with-the-aeropress-aeropress-video-tutorial/" rel="nofollow">described here</a>
) pour the beans in and then slowly pour water.</p>
<p>Let sit for 1 min ensure you've filled to the 3.5 line in the aeropress. After 1 min, apply "the btopro method" which is to press coffee to the 3 line (so .5 lines) to obtain suction, then slowly pull up on the brewer pump. (wwwhhaaaaa you say?)</p>
<a href="https://giphy.com/embed/91fEJqgdsnu4E" rel="nofollow">https://giphy.com/embed/91fEJqgdsnu4E</a>
<p>If successful, you will be able to pull air up from the cup through the filter without it moving, keeping a seal with the beans so that nothing leaks through but air pulses through the upper portions of the bean mash. This maximizes flavor... big time.</p>
<p>after plunger reaches the top of the cup, stop and press down to the 1.5 line. Then slowly pull the plunger back up, and add additional water. Continue doing this until you've used all the water in the Bonavita; ensuring that you keep the temp at 195 the whole time</p>
<p>Press till your cup is full; hopefully being able to run out of water and press all the way to the bottom. The last 5% the press can go down will pull extra oils out of the coffee beans (and believe me, with <a href="https://twitter.com/DeathWishCoffee" rel="nofollow">@DeathWishCoffee</a>
 you'll want the oils). And now, 1 last step (whhaaaa?)</p>
<a href="https://giphy.com/embed/tu54GM19sqJOw" rel="nofollow">https://giphy.com/embed/tu54GM19sqJOw</a>
<p>Get ANOTHER cup of similar size (or slightly larger), and slowly pour your full cup of coffee into this one until you hit about 95% empty. Very, slowly pour this last amount and you'll be able to trap any excessive sediment added via "the btopro method" and discard.</p>
<p>And now. You have the ultimate cup of home brewed coffee. Perfect for enjoying while the kids are napping and you write an excessively long series of tweets about how you typically spend 15 minutes making a cup of coffee much to the critique of everyone you know and love.
Fin.</p>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>item-c9e2488a-44dd-f0d4-4b3f-651245add81a</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 15:29:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Watch the ripples and you'll miss the waves</title>
      <link>watch-the-ripples-and-you-ll-miss-the-waves-2</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p class="hax-active"><br/></p>
<lrndesign-blockquote author="- the forgotten" display-mode="hypercard" resource="#7bbfaf23-0684-72a0-b188" prefix="oer:http://oerschema.org/ schema:http://schema.org/ dc:http://purl.org/dc/terms/ foaf:http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/ cc:http://creativecommons.org/ns# bib:http://bib.schema.org ">  <span>"I don't understand why you give this stuff away, it's worth a lot. I mean screw capitalism, yea I get it I mean right there. But Universities pay a lot of money for these things. Why make them for free? How does that get you rich"</span>
</lrndesign-blockquote>
<p>
It's not the first time it's come up, though this was definitely a more direct line of questioning then is typical. It's these promptings though that convince me [sic] that we live in a simulation, or at least that I am. Nothing else could explain why these mile markers are placed in my path except divine intervention (which a simulation would surely be someone more powerful then us placing the VR googles on the Matrix bodies; but to be less silly...)
We are reaching a critical inflection point in the near future. The point of singularity where I don't know where the road goes. It's one thing to project in 2015 the things we'd be working on by 2020. It's another to present an idea and call it Structured Anarchy about the systematic messiness of application development in institutions (education being just one). And.. it's an entirely different feeling and experience living the pieces falling into place. Seeing the alliances and relationships form, feeling the momentum (of what?) and the hair on the back of your neck stand up in disbelief that things could keep going the way they have been going. As we progress, let me assure you of one thing:</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-this-was-all-according-to-plan" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#this-was-all-according-to-plan"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
<em>This was all according to plan.</em>
</h2>
<p>See, it's like the human genome project. It takes years of effort to get the first 1% done and then after that a long time but less so to get to 2%. Then, after hitting that critical theashold (whatever it is, 10% we'll say) the rest is finished in a matter of weeks. How is this possible? There are 100 things and you did 10 in x time, the other 90 will surely take x*9.
It's because programming (and deprogramming in the case of genome) can stack and repurpose knowledge and capabilities. Unlike lifting 100 boxes one at a time into a truck, with patterned software development once we lift 1 box we've liften 10. And once we lift 10 boxes we now can lift 100. The pattern of exponential growth in capability to solve problems is because of the field itself. You solve one problem in a modular way, you roll out the modular way in a pattern, and now you've got an exponential amount of capability just in that one problem space. Now modularly solve the next, and the problem those create, and combine these solutions to solve that one. Suddenly your exponential capabilities are solving things exponentially.
It doesn't happen over night. These things take a very, very long time to develop. When I think back to the first outline designer I made it's hilarious. I "knew javascript" enough to slap some code together; but I couldn't make new code. I couldn't design things well beyond what I could do in MS paint. I didn't have version control. I didn't have a method of getting feedback and testing aside from hitting refresh tons of times.
Now, I saw a huge aspect of the problem space solved in a single day. Is it because we already built that and now know what it is? Partly yes, past knowledge of the problem helps frame future solutions for sure. But the libraries and techniques we can now leverage mean that when we solve 1 problem (say... a button design) we're now solving that "problem" in every future project we take on. In this way, things that once took weeks and months of development (I'm not talking planning / ideating, coding, typing things, testing, etc) now can be done in hours and days.
This is because our backend modularity and pattern based design now has a place on the front-end thanks to Webcomponents. Now we can pattern based deploy our modular front-end assets. Meaning that when we make a button better, we've made them all better. Meaning that when we need to build a new thing, the button can be assumed. Now button sounds small (and it is) but let's replace button with modal, card, menu, block, layout, grid system, navigation pattern, form entry method, json data loading, ANYTHING. ANY. THING. If we can build it as a component then we can repurpose it into others. This almost doesn't feel like coding based on how coding has felt the last 10 years, this feels like building things with legos (and I looooooved legos growing up).</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-tiny-things" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#tiny-things"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Tiny things</h2>
<p>So while we trickle out small pieces (a <a href="https://github.com/LRNWebComponents/lrnsys-outline">outline</a>
, a <a href="https://github.com/LRNWebComponents/responsive-grid">grid system</a>
, a <a href="https://github.com/LRNWebComponents/pdf-element">PDF</a>
, a <a href="https://github.com/LRNWebComponents/paper-audio-player">mp3 player</a>
, a <a href="https://github.com/LRNWebComponents/video-player">video player</a>
, a <a href="https://github.com/LRNWebComponents/lrndesign-gallery">gallery</a>
, the list goes on) that's not really what we're building. These are just by-products of our new found capabilities. We don't have just these either. We've got <a href="https://github.com/LRNWebComponents">122 repos of these little pieces</a>
 and these are just the ones we've shared so far. When we get into full on apps (powering parts of elmsln) there are another 10 full on headless applications that are running there.
These little pieces; these little things. While we've been putting out these ripples (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dhD6Y77eXmc" rel="nofollow">and some are very cool</a>
) I implore you not to focus on them. But look out a bit further and see the tidal wave that's brewing. A wave which I assure you, is coming a shore soon.</p>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>item-fd7f3b3e-edbb-ea0f-fc85-717973f49cb0</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 15:29:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I challenge you to Transform Education; together</title>
      <link>i-challenge-you-to-transform-education-together-2</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>Institutions and employees within them will remain at rest unto acted upon by an internal or external force. Externally, this is the preasures of society, markets and learners demanding change. Internally, this is tempored radicals within the machine knowing the machine needs to change. But change is more complex then that, because preasures for change and the path toward change are not linear. It also means those with motivations to not remain at rest will exponentially increase in their ability to not stay at rest. One innovation after immense frustration kicks off dozens as opposed to one leading to one more.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-the-btopro-flow-of-educational-innovation" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#the-btopro-flow-of-educational-innovation"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
The Btopro Flow of Educational Innovation</h2>
<p><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="innovation.jpg"><img src="innovation.jpg" alt="Btopro's Flow of Educational Innovation" style="max-width:100%;"/></a>

In my spectrum of educational innovation, I place Ease of the staff to manage on the same axes as frustration. Something is either easy or difficult, not much to note there. Vertically we see Sameness and Innovation. Now, The easier something is, the more the same it will remain. Once we've transitioned a technology to a resting state, say ethernet cable in the walls for Fiber connectivity, then we'd like it to remain the same and be easy to maintain (I know network engineers will say it's actually frustrating as hell and the same but let's imagine here). Once that technology is at rest and stabilized, we really don't want there to be innovation in that space.
Innovation, both it's pursuit and what it takes to pursue, is a different animal. Innovation forces the individual and the organization to strive toward frustration. Frustration and perserverence lead to growth. For example, backend application development is very difficult at first. But once one masters MySQL and PHP (as examples), and then masters Ubuntu (operating system); now, the frustration subsides and the exponential inversion of the frustration, arching towards innovation can occur. And not just occur, but do so at scale.</p>
<h3><a id="user-content-virtualization" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#virtualization"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Virtualization</h3>
<p>Another example. Now that you've mastered PHP/MySQL to make the underpinnings of an application. And Ubuntu for it to ride on. Learning Docker and doing something meaningful with it is relatively trivial. Using knowledge of Docker, you can virtualize and deploy the once impossibly complex and frustrating task, an infinite number of times. Your command of 1 application was greater effort then the now command of 1000s. And this, from an organizational perspective, is what leads to transformation.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-the-pathway-to-transformation" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#the-pathway-to-transformation"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
The pathway to transformation</h2>
<p>What process are you engaged in now that will keep things the same? Is it reliance on legacy solutions? Perhaps staffing that "won't get us there" (whatever there is). Then it's possible you should accept your sameness and relegate the easy, stationary tasks to those that work there now. You must achieve stability with those best suited for stability. (note the bold) <em>This is also an incredibly important function of any organization. Without sameness, without ease of management, you do not have an organization to manage.</em>

But the process of transformation of practice, of digging in and fundamentally enhancing what was frustrating into what is now easy (and eventually the same even if previously infinitely difficult) is a different task. It's not the same. It's not better, it's not worse. There may be more conferences to submit to and it might have more "glory" as we as humans tend to glorify and appreciate different and new more then old and stable. However, these are two very different car engines : innovation, and sameness.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-two-engines" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#two-engines"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Two engines</h2>
<p>It's critical that we as bringers of the new digital revolution realize this. If we are to bring our institutions into the future, we need a different set of engines in order to do so. You don't replace the HVAC system with a next generation HVAC system while maintaining the current one. You maintain the current one, explore new ones, and then when the time is right, start to make the switch. <em>We need to focus our organizations on the future and dedicate thought leadership and technical expertise specifically toward that</em>
. Where are we going is just as critical as having those maintain where we collectively are now.
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="ana-gabriel-9811.jpg"><img src="ana-gabriel-9811.jpg" alt="Leading out of the cave" style="max-width:100%;"/></a>

<a href="https://unsplash.com/@agabriel?utm_medium=referral&utm_campaign=photographer-credit&utm_content=creditBadge" title="Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from Ana Gabriel" rel="nofollow">
<span>
</span></a>
</p>
<a href="https://unsplash.com/@agabriel?utm_medium=referral&utm_campaign=photographer-credit&utm_content=creditBadge" title="Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from Ana Gabriel" rel="nofollow">
<title>unsplash-logo</title>



<span>Ana Gabriel</span>
</a>
<a href="https://unsplash.com/@wes_c?utm_medium=referral&utm_campaign=photographer-credit&utm_content=creditBadge" title="Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from Wes Carpani" rel="nofollow">
<span>

<title>unsplash-logo</title>


</span>
<span>Wes Carpani</span>
</a>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>item-40122e25-5673-4544-133f-2acb042dbb23</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 15:29:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NGDLE, OER, Cost reduction, accessibility and Decentralization: the future of our institutions.</title>
      <link>ngdle-oer-cost-reduction-accessibility-and-decentralization-the-future-of-our-institutions-2</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p></p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>item-1851779a-7fe1-2fa1-ddd5-0a926467a3e3</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 15:29:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Actually, curing edtech</title>
      <link>actually-curing-edtech-2</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p class="highlight"><span class="dropcaps dropcaps-i">I</span> read an article recently by <a href="https://er.educause.edu/articles/2017/4/the-rise-of-educational-technology-as-a-sociocultural-and-ideological-phenomenon" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">Educause Review</a>
 and I wonder if your able to pick up on what I did. Before reading ahead, take a minute and read through their article. It's a good take on the state of affairs in education as it relates to edtech...</p>
<h2>Ding</h2>
<p>Ok class, pencils down. Now; Who can tell me what is wrong with the following argument?</p>
<ul><li>We live in a techno-centric worldview where technology is the driver of outcomes</li>

<li>Education is historically non-profit driven, while technology is profit driven</li>

<li>Therefore, part of the commoditization of education can be attributed to edtech</li>

<li>
<em>To fix this we recommend kindly helping to inform our edtech overlords sliiiightly better in theory to maaaaaybe help us actually have the thing we want</em>

<h2>We ask stations to pause for a moment of head-esplod-ification</h2>

<p>What, the, actually F is that!? So let me get this straight. Education is important as a social good, it's something that generally speaking still isn't completely driven by a pure profit motive. It's situated somewhere between socialist utopia (Everyone has access <em>maaaan</em>
) and capitalist utopia (Everyone competes and knowledge is part of that competition). And you address concerns of "Weeellll it seems like these technology vendors have no real foundation in education / instructional principles" with the equivalent of the "meh" emoji followed by a hands up in the air?
I read this article and went off on a total drill down rant on twitter (unfortunately against someone who's an edtech provider and he wasn't the target it just sorta happened that way). They for once, finally, omg finally identify the problem: That edtech producers don't work in Education and have almost no clue wtf they are doing other then making something shiny. There is little to no research behind what they do. <strong>AND THEY ARE PURELY PROFIT DRIVEN</strong>
. So check, check, check and then your conclusion is... but oh well, let's keep on keeping on while acknolwedging this is the case.
<em>{deep breathe}</em>
</p>

<h2>NOOOO.</h2>

<p>You will not fix the problem of a techno-centric society driven education further to the brink through edtech (article's point, not mine) BY REPEATING THE SAME DAMN PATTERN WE HAVE BEEN. Stop. Stop with this bullshit narrative that magically those in silicon valley, or worse, the very students you bring in to train, build up the knowledge of and send out the door are some how inherently supporior at the production of educational technology then the institutions that are doing the training!
This false narrative is what perpetuates the cycles of us training people, them leaving and immediately forming companies with knowledge of our problem space and then selling us into insane contracts for things that aren't actually hitting the mark.</p>

<h2>Don't believe me?</h2>

<p>Instructure, all the rage with C levels becasue they adopted Twitter Boostrap and React in a world driven by home-made solutions, did just that. A bunch of students said "blackboard sucks" and threw something together rather quickly which is superior to it. Think for a second then... why can't we collectively do the same? NO! </p>

<h2>Why can't we do better then that?</h2>

<p>If you want to stop edtech driving us around collectively and being part of the techno-centric worldview that forces education to be more about money then learning, then you've gotta defeat this narrative. I view our team and those we collaborate with as being among the first to plant that flag in the ground. We are educators, trainers, designers, technologists, students, learners, and administrators all working together with a singular purpose to solve this problem. We are going to deliver solutions that are not profit motive driven, that are more open, more accessible, <em>have research backing</em>
, and are ultimately better then anything you will see produced external to education.</p>

<h2>Don't believe it?</h2>

<p>Watch us! This is just a small glimpse of what we have coming to all systems near you..</p>

<div class="fluid-width-video-wrapper" style="padding-top: 56.25%;"><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/videoseries?list=PLJQupiji7J5dqyIVrKfPOujZKuqbmgJKm" frameborder="0" gesture="media" allowfullscreen="" id="fitvid310970"></iframe>
</div>

</li>

</ul>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>item-4080a73d-360e-7a65-131b-705b8c6169e7</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 15:29:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In my own words: Zero cost education.</title>
      <link>in-my-own-words-zero-cost-education-2</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p></p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>item-1f14703a-1e61-d454-f03a-52a94333e9d1</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 15:29:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Education, Technology... Action.</title>
      <link>education-technology-action-2</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p></p> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>item-bea307e8-0af9-4518-dc18-c5323302165c</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 15:29:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pure Joy</title>
      <link>pure-joy-2</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>The family gathered, friends came and we all shared a laugh.</p>
<p>Then, he pulled me aside. My oldest was concerned as to why he wasn't getting ready for bed yet. "I have to start getting ready for bed can I brush my teeth?" A 7 year old is never one to demand they be put to bed when up snacking and well, not sleeping. But this wasn't an average day. This was December 24th.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-why-do-you-want-to-get-ready-for-bed" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#why-do-you-want-to-get-ready-for-bed"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
"Why do you want to get ready for bed?"</h2>
<h2><a id="user-content-because-i-have-to-get-ready-for-bed-and-go-to-sleep-so-santa-can-come-at-midnight" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#because-i-have-to-get-ready-for-bed-and-go-to-sleep-so-santa-can-come-at-midnight"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
"Because, I have to get ready for bed and go to sleep so Santa can come at Midnight!"</h2>
<p>He was very excited for Christmas this year, more so then any previous. His cousin was in town, his brother was also at an age he could grasp the brevity of the day. It is among the peak of the family joy meter when it comes to kiddo happiness.
He laid down and made me rush through prayers because he had to go to sleep. He is a wonderful, funny, thoughtful little boy; and after all the hours worked, time on this machine worked, it is incredibly rewarding to sit back and watch them. I'm not taking these years for granted, I know they are fleeting; I can barely hold my boys at night to put into bed or rock them to calm down after a bad dream.</p>
<p>I got my wife a book this year called <em>The Book of Happiness</em>
. And it's a large, blank book. It's a replica from the movie Up that the main character and his wife build and I was going to write in it but instead, I left it blank. Because it's not my story to write and build; It's our story, and the pages of our lives we write together are the ones we need to document together. The smiles from a surprise trip, or a long awaited one, the tokens of places visited, artwork, treasures. These are all we'll have left one day. Not the presents, the wrapping, the food; just the few single pages of the incredible story we wrote together.</p>
<p>Right now though, we're in the think of our story. I pray our pages are many in this book, but no matter what the ending, these will always be years colored with pure golden sunshine. The light that only children bring to our lives as parents. The golden years of our little family growing together, as we all get to be apart of a memorable phenomena:
<em><strong>Pure Joy</strong>
</em>
.</p>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>item-897d5115-b6de-2c55-afa7-ba3262f4d9ca</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 15:29:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Creating the decentralized instructional experience app</title>
      <link>creating-the-decentralized-instructional-experience-app-2</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>This is based on a submission to the Penn State open innovation challenge for 2018. I like to post my ideas to my blog in addition to my submission so that I never lose them. This one is about the logical extension to HAX for desktop over 2018 which could be utilized to decentralize instructional experience creation. If this sounds of use to your institution, good, let's work together on it.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-problem" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#problem"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Problem</h2>
<p>Faculty and staff have no idea what they can use at our institution. No matter how many registries of information or solutions we provide, people will need to practically be marketted to just to know they exist in the sea of information about what makes the university work. Beyond this, there is no way to provide continuous innovation to those not at high-touch units which work hand in hand with faculty to produce highly experimental course spaces and approaches. Even if we could find the things we need, very few of them talk to each other, their user experiences are all over the map, and most aren't very good for creating materials without needing to understand technical topics (like HTML). This isn't a PSU specific problem, Duke has an illustration that highlights 93+ solutions available to faculty, many of which don't talk even if they knew them all.
How to solve the problem of finding and once getting there creating engaging experiences?</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-leading-questions" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#leading-questions"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Leading questions</h2>
<ul>
<li>What if faculty and staff involved in producing instructional experiences had an app that told them what services existed and made it instantly possible to use?</li>

<li>What would it look like institutionally and what would the use experience look like?</li>

<li>What needs would we have technically in order to support this?</li>

</ul>
<h2><a id="user-content-vision" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#vision"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Vision</h2>
<p>This is the vision of HAX, a distributed instructional creation tool. <a href="http://haxtheweb.org/" rel="nofollow">HAX can be viewed as a public demo here</a>
. The important thing to keep in mind with this is that desktop publishing of applications can be done using HTML, making them far easier to build when you just make it work on the web. Imagine if users could log into the app on their laptop or phone and just create. Creating a new course? Start one on your local machine and with the press of a button publish it to Canvas, Drupal, ELMS:LN, GravCMS or a static website. Want to see what colleagues have shared from their courses? Fork their materials by searching an institution protected repository right from the app or connect to global shared object repositories. Instead of trying to market to faculty and staff what services are available, have people utilize a unified app which connects to the registry of everything available to them for teaching and learning.
Want to stream video? Upload it to the app and it'll publish it to youtube or the video provider the university supports. Want to create H5P but don't understand hosting? Build it in the app and it'll save to the correct, FERPA valid location. Want to create a slideshow? Drag and drop a series of images which automatically get uploaded to Amazon S3 and then click a UI to "build" your slideshow. Worry about accessibility? HAX will take care of it for you automatically and without the ability to make in-accessible content. Content in HAX is accessible by default due to the game changing technology called <a href="https://www.webcomponents.org/" rel="nofollow">webcomponents</a>
.
Let's get faculty and staff out of the business of understanding HTML and instead build materials that allow them to leverage the services the institution provides without increased cognitive load.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-2018" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#2018"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
2018</h2>
<p>The ELMS:LN team has begun work on such a desktop app called <a href="https://github.com/LRNWebComponents/hax-desktop-app">HAX deskop app</a>
 which seeks to achieve this vision. Help us make this a reality in 2018 and beyond as we seek to empower faculty and align technology deployments with academic freedom and student curiosity.</p>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>item-70c61ad7-f543-9af8-dd1b-1b65f0f453b2</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 15:29:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>This is not reality</title>
      <link>this-is-not-reality-2</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <h2><a id="user-content-chapter-1-the-shower" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#chapter-1-the-shower"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Chapter 1: The Shower</h2>
<p>A Developer takes a shower. A Developer closes his eyes, breathes deeply, and presses the water over his scalp and eyes and face. When hands press against the eye socket in the pressense of light, synapese fire off randomly. These random firings of "light" dance in the retina of the Developer seeking the answer to a problem. The retinas of the developer see the sparks trickel away as color fades back in.
The developer pauses.. then does it again, this time focusing on those whips of ocular static fizzle away. The whips form a pattern that looks like a central star that everything is firing out and away, creating their own central stars to fire out and away from. The occular misfires form a fractual image in the minds eye.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-chapter-2-the-fractal" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#chapter-2-the-fractal"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Chapter 2: The fractal</h2>
<p>The developer talks through how a fractal could be used in the design of a system. The developer writes down the fractal. The developer sees a video the next day expressing, visually, the concept of divergent ideas spawning ohter divergent ideas, expressed as a series of hexagons firing off at a tangent and forming new hexagons. The developer recreates the pattern on a whiteboard and begins to theorize how this pattern could be used to represent systems.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-chapter-3-the-monster-within" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#chapter-3-the-monster-within"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Chapter 3: The monster within</h2>
<p>The developer explains this to one other person over two hours. The manager is excited but leaves with: "Who else would ever understand how any of this works though." The developer smiles, "I guess I'll just have to build it to find out". The developer works on prototypes, burning through hundreds of hours beyond what normal projects there are to pursue. The idea is like a dagger in his mind. He starts shutting down from the rest of the world and focusing solely on this one idea. This one fractal.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-chapter-4-the-friend" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#chapter-4-the-friend"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Chapter 4: The friend</h2>
<p>He explains an early prototype to a friend. The friend is intrigued but doesn't get it or see how it's the fractal. The developer keeps pushing on, convinced there is a fractal there. The developer makes prototype after prototype, pouring through hours of tutorials and producing posts and videos looking for someone to understand what he's claiming to have discovered. No one gets it. Again, and again, over the next 2 years, the developer repeats this cycle, trying desperately to get someone to understand the picture in his mind now layed out as code and directory trees. Symlinks and .gitignores. But no one. Gets it.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-chapter-5-the-group" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#chapter-5-the-group"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Chapter 5: The group</h2>
<p>Until... Someone does. Two people actually. And then from two, three, and three, four; and four, five; and five, a dozen, and dozens. Until the fractal no longer is some obscure concept it's the way of visualizing and attacking the problem. The Developer is no longer a developer, and no longer is a young developer either...</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-chapter-6-the-team" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#chapter-6-the-team"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Chapter 6: The team</h2>
<p>The Developer is part of a team. A Team hell bent on innovation. A Team that doesn't accept the world and the educational system the way it is but dreams of what it can be, what it will be. A Team that believes education is not a pidgenholed public service job but the place that fosters and grows innovations of it's own. A Team believes that noone is better then the sun of it's parts.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-chapter-7-the-way-forward" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#chapter-7-the-way-forward"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Chapter 7: The way forward</h2>
<p>A Team of Developers, instructors, instructional designers, designers, students, management; of mixed talents and backgrounds and abilities, form a new fractal pattern within a traditionally stasis laden system.</p>
<h2><a id="user-content-chapter-8-the-upside-down" class="anchor" aria-hidden href="#chapter-8-the-upside-down"><svg class="octicon octicon-link" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" height="16" aria-hidden><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M4 9h1v1H4c-1.5 0-3-1.69-3-3.5S2.55 3 4 3h4c1.45 0 3 1.69 3 3.5 0 1.41-.91 2.72-2 3.25V8.59c.58-.45 1-1.27 1-2.09C10 5.22 8.98 4 8 4H4c-.98 0-2 1.22-2 2.5S3 9 4 9zm9-3h-1v1h1c1 0 2 1.22 2 2.5S13.98 12 13 12H9c-.98 0-2-1.22-2-2.5 0-.83.42-1.64 1-2.09V6.25c-1.09.53-2 1.84-2 3.25C6 11.31 7.55 13 9 13h4c1.45 0 3-1.69 3-3.5S14.5 6 13 6z"></path>
</svg>
</a>
Chapter 8: The upside down</h2>
<p>The Developer is no longer alone in the wilderness. The Developer is now part of the Team poised to change education, and the world. Join <em>us</em>
.</p>
<iframe src="https://www.elmsln.org/stranger-things/" width="100%" height="500px"></iframe>
<a href="https://www.elmsln.org/stranger-things/">Stranger Things...</a>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>item-be6f30a2-8a4d-e986-6af3-930f91e00464</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 15:29:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When Educators left the LMS</title>
      <link>when-educators-left-the-lms-2</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p class="highlight"><span class="dropcaps dropcaps-w">W</span>hile not seeing it beyond previews and reviews, the movie <a href="https://www.amazon.com/When-Left-Building-Group-Productions/dp/1470742136" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">When God left the building</a>
 reviews an intreging concept: that people who leave the christian church are just leaving the building and pursuing God in ways that connect better with them. I bring this idea up because I see parallels with instructors and the building provided for them, the learning management system.
As someone who works on the side of building tools to escape the monotony; I can see both sides. Staff, instructional or otherwise, tend to want people to use the same thing. This helps from a support perspective; I mean, it's hard to support people in lots of tools, especially those unknown to the support staff. Faculty on the other hand, at times, want control and the freedom to use whatever they want in order to properly teach the subject in question.</p>
<p class="highlight">How best to reach these people?
If we just funnel more functionality into a learning management system, they aren't coming back. Sometimes it's far more than just the fact that the LMS doesn't provide the capabilities they need; it's a fundamental distrust of a system who's three letter acronym invokes feelings of rage in many. It is also, even if unknowingly, a stand against authoritan system integrations (<em>huh?</em>
).
When a solution, any solution, is promoted by an organization as the one source of truth; some will naturally have an affinity towards literally anything else. The positioning of the system as the one and only, is a pure authoritarian stance; we must have control of this transaction (even if just in perception). Academia is built on the principle of exploration, academic freedom, and diversity. It has many libertarian and socialist leanings just in its positioning in society (education for all, freedom to explore and expand thought). These two forces; the deployment of centralized, singular solutions, is by default antithetical to the institutions which they are deployed within.
So what to do? Well, this is where I can confuse many at times since I'm perceived as having my own LMS (it's not but that's ok). <em>Speaks directly to faculty</em>
: I want you to use whatever makes the most sense for you, that teaches your subject matter in the way that makes the most impact, and that doesn't cripple you financially or grading wise to utilize. Maximum freedom; what we produce or otherwise. However; where this stance differs is this: While the Church of LMS wants you to come back and retain membership as the one pathway to educational success. ELMS:LN spins off technologies into spheres outside of the traditional LMS church in order to meet you where it made sense for you.
You want to have your own content outside of any system? There's a project for that, and we'll make it easy to integrate afterwards. YOU are in control, we adapted to you. It's just a small part of why we build software completely outside of an LMS context which can build up the educational prowess of other solutions.
Take our latest content authoring experience we've been working on - <a href="http://haxtheweb.org" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">HAX</a>
. This is ELMS:LN's next generation authoring solution.... built entirely outside of ELMS; in fact at the moment, it's not talking to anything it's just a static website. Why? Let's cover just a few of the "targets" this can then radically transform into educational technology:</p>
<ul>
<li>Any CMS that integrates HAX (which currently Drupal 7, Drupal 8, Backdrop, and GravCMS are all on the roadmap)</li>

<li>Static webpages / single page demonstrations which can be identical in every way to the real thing</li>

<li><a href="https://github.com/LRNWebComponents/hax-desktop-app" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">Desktop publishing</a>
 to do everything completely offline or via local development</li>

<li><em>any LMS that wants to have an authoring experience second to none</em>
</li>

<li>any tool that doesn't fit into those buckets or other solution that needs a flexible editor</li>

<li><a href="/blog/the-day-educators-left-the-lms/www.elmsln.org">ELMS:LN</a>

By creating an authoring experience for the production of educational materials or otherwise (It's a really nice website builder at minimum), we can reduce the cost of producing a high quality webpage (it's doing 3D rendering in the browser w/ VR I mean come on now!) and can also hook it up with all kind of meta-data that education needs (ala <a href="/blog/the-day-educators-left-the-lms/oerschema.org">OERSchema</a>
). We can improve the quality of production, decrease cost of production, and do it in a uniform method no matter where it's been deployed. This is bringing church to people. It's connecting with them in the way they need because they have unique needs (snokeflake logo). It's the complete opposite stance of the LMS which says "Integrate with me, I am the one great source of truth".
Because much like the emptying buildings in the film, it's not that Educators left education, they just will start teaching and educating in other ways and in other places. Because when everything can be a learning experience, we no longer need a dedicated building to provide it to us.</li>

</ul>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>item-46aa6443-ebf1-62b2-6523-760490d5ce9b</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 15:29:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Singularity, Digital Activism, and saving our institutions</title>
      <link>singularity-digital-activism-and-saving-our-institutions-2</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p class="highlight">*This talk was originally posted on elmsln.org. I've removed it there and moved it here because even though it's about Drupal / ELMSLN, it's the first talk I gave that I started speaking my mind and talking about the bit-coin-ization of the world and structures that aren't sustainable.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>How can projects like ELMSLN improve the public sector and help transform our interactions with institutions? How can we bring about more collaboration that is peer to peer and institution to institution? These are some of the concepts that ELMSLN lead developer @btopro wrestles with daily.  Watch this rebroadcast of his DrupalCamp Wisconsin (2014) message to kickstart the day.</p>
<video-player lang="en" preload="metadata" source="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-5KGGEwerJU" sticky-corner="top-right" youtube-id="-5KGGEwerJU" iframed source-type="youtube" is-a11y-media is-youtube></video-player>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>item-92c8d1d5-e579-930b-2c57-e9753e9dfefe</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 15:29:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Organic Deployment Architecture</title>
      <link>organic-deployment-architecture-2</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <full-width-image source="files/3f7119c8ee0795b23c3ed754c7e48860e8ad8b98-organic.jpg" caption="Organic" style="width: 50%;"></full-width-image>
<h3>Decentralized deployment architecture</h3>
<p class="highlight"><span class="dropcaps dropcaps-a">A</span>ll deployments currently imply a central authority, whether a company or developer running some kind of master system with control over the rest of the network. This implies control structures which could align with the <a href="legacy-human-hierarchy">human hierarchy, a thing we've placed in legacy</a>


.</p>
<p>In order to subvert existing human hierarchies, we need technology that doesn't operate like humans do..well, not in their whole being. We need to look to organic chemistry. A virus, an infection, something that can replicate itself and spread. Less the negative connotations of disease and more the biological process of cell replication. Yes, we'll still have to have central listings of some form. The internet has DNS, indicating where the distributed some things are located (as does TOR). So we'll need repositories of some kind in order to ensure the authenticity of the package (GitHub, rpm's and what not) but by intentionally creating an organic deployment methodology, we can avoid the emergence of <strong>control</strong>


.</p>
<p>Now it's not that order is a bad thing. Surely order has given rise to the great (and fading) civilizations that we find ourselves in today (whatever the day is, we'll make new ones if these constructs fail us). But nature can break through and change society where code wrapped in business logic cannot. We need to liberate and decentralize; so less twitter (distributed as it may be, it is the only broker of tweets) and more email (truly distributed throughout the world and without ownership on the standard).</p>
<h3> </h3>
<h3>Traditional Deployments (modern day)</h3>
<p></p>
<figure class="image" style="width: 100%;"><img alt="Products live in containers next to each other without knowledge of whos who." src="files/container.jpg" style="width: 100%; height: 236px; float: left; border-width: 1px; border-style: solid; margin: 5px;"/><figcaption>Products live in containers next to each other without knowledge of whos who.</figcaption>


</figure>
<p></p>
<p>Modern deployments use <a href="https://www.docker.com/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">docker</a>


 or <a href="http://www.vmware.com/products/nsx/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">some form of virtualization</a>


. They effectively take the ins and outs of an application, tokenize them, and then slap them up in "the cloud" (AWS... all of them). Once there, when you buy into a product, they basically are just making you a containerized instance on AWS and charging you overhead. SaaS works because you are lazy (we all are) and we like having the simplicity of someone else taking out our garbage rather then us having to haul it to the dump every week.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, <em>this puts us in the passenger seat to innovation</em>


. By giving up the routine of the garbage, we're beholden to the collection and disposal patterns of the garbage men. We don't need to worry ourselves with innovation, they'll ensure trash A gets to dump site B, now turn off your brain and start printing money on your existing workflows.</p>
<h3> </h3>
<h3>Grabbing control</h3>
<p>By taking control, we are taking on risk (in the short-term) in order to gain creative direction in the future. Perhaps we no longer want to shill garbage, perhaps we want to recycle methane off-gasing of shallowly dug dump sites while utilizing solar powered vehicles. We now have that level of creative control. But unlike this fictitious scenario, we don't have to worry ourselves with the mechanisms involved; it's technology, and containerized technology at that; We can do (and scale) anything.</p>
<p>Containerizing, and for this definition I'm using I mean <strong>using separate hardware per client</strong>


, is the way to increase innovation as well as reduce risk. We can keep existing systems in place with existing client bases while driving forward with new, innovative clients that have unique needs, without worry of corrupting the successes of yesteryear.</p>
<p>But what if we wanted to take containerization a step further. What if we containerized different aspects of existing clients, enabling us to innovate more rapidly even in existing client bases. But this must come at the expense of complexity and risk, right? Not if we start designing our deployments and products <em>like living things</em>


.</p>
<p> </p>
<h3>Deploying an organic compound</h3>
<p></p>
<figure class="image"><img alt="Agency of websites" src="files/agency.jpg" style="width: 300px; height: 277px; float: right; border-width: 1px; border-style: solid; margin: 5px;"/><figcaption>Agency of websites</figcaption>


</figure>
<p></p>
<p>We need to start thinking of our applications and their deployment as living things. We aren't just creating something people see on the web, we're creating engagement, uniting people across barriers and putting them in front of the information they need to live better lives. These experiences with a technology produce, in effect, <em>agency</em>


.</p>
<p>While this is not an autonomous, living, thinking organism, it is the first step towards the evolution of more complex beings. Mapping the internet to evolutionary processes, we are describing at single celled organisms. They can't do much on their own, but they are alive and mostly just react to the stimuli they are prodded with in the world.</p>
<p>When we enter input, we get reaction, etc.</p>
<p>The fun thing about living systems though and thinking about their design as such is that single celled organisms don't remain that way for long. Interestingly though, as we move up through biology, complex structures are often formed of simpler patterns repeated thousands of times.</p>
<p> </p>
<h3>Organically pattern deployments</h3>
<p>An <em>organically pattern deployment</em>


 is a system that has the capability to set it self up again. I'm not talking traditional </p>
<p></p>
<figure class="image"><img alt="Simple forms complex structures" src="files/complexlife.jpg" style="font-size: 13px; line-height: 20px; width: 250px; height: 160px; border-width: 1px; border-style: solid; margin: 5px; float: right;"/><figcaption>Simple forms complex structures</figcaption>


</figure>
<p></p>
<p>containerization where there's a host of some kind that's doing the replication. I mean, a system that is able to set itself up, and then setup replicants of itself which are fully functioning duplicates. A deployment methodology that patterns itself more off nature then our legacy human hierarchies.</p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cell_division" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">Cell division</a>


 is the biological phase when a cell grows or splits off. It is a functional replica after the initial cell structure has reached an apex through the consumption of resources. With plants; sunlight, water, minerals. In the case of system deployments this could be usage, users, and data.</p>
<p>After enough usage, users, and data have been accumulated in a single system, the system follows the natural biological process (because we are creating life) by which its time to grow. This could mean more servers, more RAM, more processors, more storage, etc. In the case of a deployment methodology though, this means that the system will imprint itself upon a new server.</p>
<p> </p>
<h3>Replication</h3>
<p></p>
<figure class="image"><img alt="Creating Life" src="files/creatinglife.jpg" style="width: 397px; height: 769px; float: left; margin: 5px; border-width: 1px; border-style: solid;"/><figcaption>Creating Life</figcaption>


</figure>
<p></p>
<p>The git repo is instructions built in that suggest how to setup a new copy of itself. Once the new copy of itself has been established, the new cell can call home to the old and ask for additional instructions. This is where we start to mirror nature in creating complexity from organized simplicity. The new cell (Cell B) is told that it was created because we need to migrate aspects of Cell A were becoming overburdened. Maybe there's too many people using function X which can be split off into a dedicated function for Cell B. Cell A then transfers everything needed to accomplish function X onto Cell B.</p>
<p>Because it's nature and we're talking about small, replicated tasks over time, it is important to note that in the evolutionary process, <em>Cell B could handle all the tasks of Cell A</em>


 (technically). The point of the Division is to create a new, more complex organism that's able to delegate functions of the being more effectively. As Cell A and B expand in capabilities, users, data and overall usage; the process could be repeated, forming a new organism that's made up of the simpler parts.</p>
<p> </p>
<h3>My work</h3>
<p>This is the direction we're taking ELMS learning network, the educational technology platform that I help drive. The system will be treated like a living thing. Through the replication of simple tasks (a system that sets itself up) and the instructions to set itself up again (its DNA) included in the repo, we can start to form fractal deployments of ELMSLN. <em>A fractal deployment could be a copy of ELMSLN that is actually several working together to form one cohesive suite of systems</em>


. Let's say there are 13 systems in ELMSLN that are discrete functionality that use RESTful web-services to talk to each other. Then these could live on 13 different servers since they are served from 13 different domains already.<img alt="" src="files/snowflake.jpg" style="font-size: 13px; line-height: 20px; width: 420px; height: 395px; margin: 5px; border-width: 1px; border-style: solid; float: right;"/></p>
<p>The organic fractal component to the ELMSLN architecture would then suggest that 13 different copies of ELMSLN could be stitched together seamlessly to act as one system to its user-base. These systems would be stood up as Cell Division from the original deployment. Using SSH keys and having access to automated DNS reconfiguration we could have the Cell A deployment actually set the rest of the network up automatically. It could, in effect, mutate from a single celled organism into a more complex one. And because it knows how it set itself up, and the rest of itself knows how it set itself up (meta), we could put in place security procedures and mechanisms that have the network act proactively. We could start to program the single celled organism to perform increasingly more autonomous tasks, which then propagate to the rest of the parts of the organism to produce exponentially more autonomy.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>At that point, we're no longer <em>just</em>


 creating software, <strong>we're creating life</strong>


.</p>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>item-2ddc5396-01fe-60fc-5c23-fa40abae58e9</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 15:29:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ministry of information</title>
      <link>ministry-of-information-2</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p class="highlight"><span class="dropcaps dropcaps-a">A</span>re we witness to 1940s style crowd manipulation through propaganda without realizing it? Have you watched the news lately? Does it go by a single day without having a "Get social" or "#HotToday" kind of story about what people are talking about on social media? Is it really, we the people talking on social media or are these social spacing being controlled by media companies helping to shape the things "everyone" is talking about. A few things to consider with Twitter for example from a financial perspective:</p>
<ol><li>It is to twitter (and Facebook and the rest)'s advantage to NOT close dead accounts in order to justify to the board how many impressions messages can get</li>
<li>It is to twitter (and the rest)'s advantage to NOT stop hate / controversial speech, trolling, etc</li>
<li>It isn't that difficult to craft a twitter bot that searches against key words and constructs simple, hateful / inciting rhetoric messages</li>
</ol>
<p>I'm not suggesting they are doing this, I'm suggesting it is in their best interest financially to continue allowing the pattern to exist. It may sound conspiratorial until you realize it's already been done before. Anyone remember <a href="http://www.thegloss.com/2014/11/03/beauty/alex-from-target-teenager-viral-internet-meme/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">#AlexFromTarget</a>
? You'll notice in that link there is no reference to what actually happened. This may have "gone viral" but there was a <a href="http://www.cnn.com/2014/11/04/living/alex-from-target/index.html" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">marketing company claiming to be pulling the strings</a>
 to prove that they can do things like this. That they can get a random person on the news and millions talking about something pointless isn't really harmful, <a href="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/jul/08/darpa-social-networks-research-twitter-influence-studies" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">but what could be is this</a>
 (and you know others are doing it too).</p>
<p>What's to say this isn't happening right now? I've been trolled by hate-bots before. Mozilla controversy? Say the word Mozilla. Drumpft? Say his name, get attacked instantly. The easiest way to stop this? Ignore those bots seeking to put you in their echo chamber of hate. It keeps you from hyping twitter (and the hate brigades) agendas and maybe, just maybe will make you have a better outlook on the world too.</p>
<p>Question everything.</p>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>item-f8a9a36b-2d96-17ec-0a07-356191bb57ff</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 15:29:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rate of perception</title>
      <link>rate-of-perception-2</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>I remember in high school talking about biology and as a test, you have to poke your arm with a small pin (lightly) and report when you can tell the difference between where it is and where your brain is telling you "Hey that's in a new place". The point was to demonstrate that our nerve endings are only so far apart and as a result only so capable of measuring change.</p>
<p>Has the same effect starting occurring to us all?</p>
<p>Have we lost the ability to detect the change in our history currently taking place. Is the saturation of information and data points due to 24/7 news, twitter's instantaneous results, devices on everywhere at all times, radio, billboards, blog posts and magazines. Have we come to a point where there is so much data we are simply filtering it all our, no longer having enough time to dig deep enough to evaluate the truthfulness of the statements?</p>
<p>When you have people lying to your face on TV and others refuting their claims, their recourse is often boiled down to "google ____ you'll see". Will you see? Will you take the time to verify claims or counter claims? Or do you do what too many do (myself included); look for the likes, hearts and retweets and use social validation as a sign of confirming correctness. Isn't that what all the others pushing that RT button did? Assume; assume with all the information they are getting bombarded with that their 20 seconds to read a tweet, process it, laugh and/or get angry and decide to RT... was this really enough to ingest, process, explore and assess?</p>
<p>Has technology eliminated our ability to do the hard work of looking.</p>
<p>It is not to blame the media, or blame the technology platforms; but it is to blame the self. Without self control, self moderation as to how much data we consume and expose ourselves to that we're losing what it is to be human. We're losing the desire to process, to go beyond simply reacting but to really, genuinely question, process, and respond (or even better, NOT respond).</p>
<p>Is there too much noise to really have things like facts matter? Are fact just what a large enough group of people say and feel? With access to so many so easily, it's easy to make the faulty assumption that quantity of agreement equates to quality of information.</p>
<p>We are a culture drunk on data, and as a result, we're not paying attention to what any of it means. Be careful who you aggregate.</p>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>item-093425c7-cba0-e10b-60f8-9bf6afd32f9a</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 15:29:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficiency as Activism</title>
      <link>efficiency-as-activism-2</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p class="highlight"><span class="dropcaps dropcaps-e">E</span>fficiency is not just the right thing to do or the act of making things better then before. Like anything, it can be a tactic if used correctly to modify structures from within. Anything done with intention is activism and so, If you don't like someone, automate them.</p>
<h3>Huh?</h3>
<p>Automate them. Do your job in 90% of the time it takes to do, use the other 10% to study and analyze their process. What is it they do? How do they make money? Now, start to carve around that person via process modification. You can intentionally disrupt their job, all the while claiming it in the name of efficiency.</p>
<h3>That's evil</h3>
<p>Yeah, kind of; but not in any way different then what happens when corporations (now called Start-Ups because it's less evil sounding) intentionally enter a space in a different way to "Disrupt" a marketplace. Efficiency is generally viewed as a social good and a net positive but it destroys ways of doing business and the humans attached to those hierarchies. Can you imagine what it must be like to have been a telephone operator and see them wheel in a machine that automatically did routing, putting 1000s out of work?</p>
<p>So, for those of you out there with root access to things; what will you do with these powers? What can you make the machine do that you cannot yet producing the same net effect? What percentage of your job can you automate in order to do other things to produce Magic?</p>
<h3>Magic?</h3>
<p>Yeah, Magic. That which we can't comprehend is indiscernible from Magic -- <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clarke%27s_three_laws" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">Clarke's three laws</a>
. I got asked this weekend when I realized I could automate and no one would notice what i was doing. I looked up and way... thought... and said... 6 years ago. I've been able to automate for about 6 years, and I have. It's why what we're doing doesn't seem believable, because I've been working on the scaffolding of what it is we're standing on today, 3 years ago. I intentionally, painfully so at times, focused on under the hood automation rather then front-facing usability. Because you can always make people like the way something looks, you can never change what it's built on top of (or at least not easily).</p>
<p>And so, when I say we can pick up and give you every innovation our group has made and let you produce new ones; and do so with exponentially increasing accuracy, capability, ease of use and ease of setup. I'm not lying, we're just making Magic, through efficiency, done so to empower others to produce innovations of their own. Ultimately seeking to boil self-empowerment down to choice. Do you copy and paste the line and liberate yourself and others? Do you help others to disrobe these cloaks, so invisibly <span style="font-size: 13px; line-height: 20px;">placed</span> upon creativity or do we continue onward without direct control of educational experiences?</p>
<h3>What is my activist intention you may ask?</h3>
<p>Empowerment. More importantly, what's yours? Who will you automate today?</p>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>item-9566b53a-7c4c-54fb-4054-390d7c4c6e2e</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 15:29:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OccuTea WallParty</title>
      <link>occutea-wallparty-2</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p class="highlight"><span class="dropcaps dropcaps-i">I</span>, much like you, am a person just trying to make sense of the world. Before you spew hate, recall this.</p>
<p>I am an observer of politics that tries to "play the game" a bit differently. There are tells at times to my "leanings" but I try very hard to make it difficult to understand how I view the world or who I stand with. As a result, I follow many people on both "sides" of many issues. I follow people of many parties, view points, and affiliations in order to better understand (140 characters at a time mind you) how they try to draw support for their truth being more correct then others. In doing this, I've identified a common thread that should form the 3rd major political party, but hasn't (yet) because the other two require us all to be divided (it sells better on the news).</p>
<p>Let's abstract potentially negative messaging and viewpoints; what common threads exist between the two "extremist" (media deemed, not my own) political movements that make up both "major" political parties? Because if we study and understand the concerns of the "extremists" maybe we can figure out how to form a new camp that encompasses both.</p>
<p>Two candidates right now are offshoots of grassroots activism the last decade.</p>
<h3>Occupy</h3>
<p>Bernie Sanders probably immediately comes to mind if you follow or believe in this political movement. It's largely (but not exclusively) thought of as:</p>
<ul><li>Banks are corrupt</li>
<li>Tax policy isn't tipped in the favor of the little guy</li>
<li>The system is rigged so the rich keep getting richer</li>
<li>Minorities are especially excluded and abused by this system of control</li>
<li>We are in endless wars we have no business being in</li>
<li>Politics needs reform to prevent corruption</li>
</ul>
<p>In this world view, Banks and The Rich are largely thought of as the source of corruption so we need government to be brought back into control of the people in order to eliminate the corruption.</p>
<h3>Tea</h3>
<p>There are several Republican figures that come to mind when the Tea Party is evoked but based on the principles of less government involvement, lower taxes and anti-corruption I'd have to say Ted Cruz is the spokesperson. Bullet points here:</p>
<ul><li>Government is too big and corrupt (as a result)</li>
<li>Taxes are too high (as a result of too big bureaucracy)</li>
<li>The system is rigged, political elites keep getting richer</li>
<li>Everyone is abused by this system</li>
<li>Politics needs reform to prevent corruption</li>
<li>In this world view, Government and hierarchies are largely to blame, not them in and of themselves, but because of the types of people that find their way into these hierarchies. For example, a complex tax code leads to it being written in a way to benefit some and not others.</li>
</ul>
<p>I largely ignore social issues in analysis and selection on candidates. It's weird to say but I've seen that social change is enacted from pressures from society as a whole. As a result, the rising up of people that are passionate about change is how to enact social change.</p>
<h3>This is 2016</h3>
<p>With the internet, with technology, with all our capabilities to spread positivity, crowd fund and disseminate information; how are we still here? A two party system with media coverage and collusion that leads us to largely all unhappy. We're allowing our media and social media to keep us apart. What can we agree on even in these two extreme propositions of Occupy and Tea Party movements.</p>
<h3>Corruption is king</h3>
<p>How can we reduce corruption? Both sides identify this but then have different views on Taxes (we aren't doing enough vs we're doing too much). This will be my tell as a classic liberal, but we need less of a system in order to have less corruption. This doesn't mean we don't need a system but we do need a less complex system (taxes and in general); and here's why.</p>
<p>If you are a developer you may have heard of "legacy code" and the need to refactor code. Unlike other resources, having more code does not equate to having more effective code. Well friends, we're running on legacy code that is in desperate need of refactorring. We've got a great operating system, but we've been adding way too much functionality and it's bringing the whole thing down. We don't need to throw away everything we've ever done, but we do need to take those concepts and completely rewrite them for the modern era.</p>
<p>Yes, Government needs it's Drupal 8 moment. Is the end product "the same"? In some ways yes. We still make a CMS, it still makes great websites and it's still responsive. But we're rooting out all the bloat that's weighing our awesome product down. We're doing things smarter, not always differently.</p>
<p>Corruption and governmental refactoring needs to be the focus of a unified movement between Occupy and Tea people. Quit arguing over social policy, quit arguing your party or person vs their party or person. Look beyond parties, look at what we're doing to our country and unite to pull us back from the edge (where edge is Fascism, rioting because of corruption, further deepening of racial divides). Quit pointing the finger and start reaching out with love. Lay down your ideologies and realize this: We are all not that different, we all want the corruption to end. Seek out those that have this message. One says we can have less corruption through regulation while the other proposes solutions that involve tearing down parts of the institution to reduce corruption though there being less of it.</p>
<p>Personally, I'm for the refactor (because where are these more perfect Angels) but align on anti-corruption and we will solve our problems.</p>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>item-f7c4705e-c70b-6cf9-0623-095830584d4d</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 15:29:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DDoSA</title>
      <link>ddosa-2</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>We live in the age of Citizen agents‏. Everyone can become their own nation state because of the authority that technology affords us. If broadcasting and viewership is validation, we all have been validated as having the ability to enact and broadcast change.</p>
<p>You may have heard of DDoS in tech news. A DDoS is a Distributed Denial of Service. Basically a whole bunch of hackers (or if you're really smart, just one infecting many systems) perpetrates a DDoS by slamming certain systems with traffic. This has other names like orbital ion cannon, ping of death and "wiping a site from the internet". Basically you keep shelling a system from so many points of entry that firewalls can't identify the traffic as the same request so it makes the servers think that there's just a lot of people accessing.</p>
<p>Today I'd like to propose a human based form of the same idea which we will dub a DDoSA - Distributed Denial of System Authority. Utilizing this technique individuals, much like a DDoS, can overwhelm a system of control with too many requests, rendering the controlling authority useless. There's too many "packets" for the organization to control which disrupts the organization's ability to effectively control the message, solutions, methods of practice, etc.</p>
<h2>Let me explain with a bad example...</h2>
<p>You are disgusted that people use Sharepoint to share documents. You suggest using DropBox but that's shut down as an individual because of security, policy, xyz. In order to correctly utilize DropBox, you don't need to go to anyone asking for permissions, you need to tell your friends to use DropBox. And then, when collaboration is through the roof and productivity is way up, you have your friends tell their friends. Soon, the entire organization is utilizing the non-standard tool in a peer-to-peer, occupy wall street fashion.</p>
<p>So does it matter if DropBox is the christened solution of the organization? No, everyone just uses it. (This is unofficial Slack channels at most companies in a nutshell) People self-organize around what works best when friction to do so is limited (internet / free technologies).</p>
<p>I often voice the opinion that policy is irrelevant in the face of automation; because, it is impossible to enforce that which automation can alleviate so easily. Make automation invisible (Slack) and highly usable (Slack) and you'll see citizen agents pop up all over the place.</p>
<p>The person that implemented Sharepoint and told others to use it has no ability to keep pace with those rapidly utilizing and encouraging others to utilize DropBox. The capabilities are far greater then SharePoint. Maybe they have greater control over their files. What ever the case, the citizen agents are a more effective marketing tool then the lone individual from on high bringing a solution into the organization.</p>
<h2>DDoSA in RL</h2>
<p>DDoSAs have other names in real life. Sit ins. Arab Spring. Occupy Movement. Flooding prisons til they are over capacity with conscientious objectors. These are all the same, just applying the tactic to different mediums. Take quantity X that has stopgap X-1. Apply X against stopgap X-1. Watch stopgap X-1 become overwhelmed because X is always greater. Far more important then authority in pulling off a DDoSA is <a href="http://buytaert.net/open-source-and-social-capital" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">social capital</a>
. Social capital, while not as quantifiable as money, is a much deeper well to draw from once filled.</p>
<p>It takes a lot longer to fill that well then making money, building social capital involves P2P connections and those take time to build (Occupy was months when at its height). But it is far more powerful then money as we move increasingly towards a block-chain-esk society (and, we are). I mean, several countries collapsed in part because of the power of the individuals that stopped believing in the authority of their governing structures.</p>
<h2>DDoSA to reclaim control</h2>
<p>The air about a situation in which you might see a DDoSA usually stems from a lack of control. Feelings of disempowerment drive some to apathy and others to organize. People strive make meaning of and be in control of the world around them. And so as our technologies get cheaper, easier, and faster they'll increasingly demand more order be established to help them pick through the chaos all around.</p>
<p>To use a DDoSA in your organization currently plagued by Slack (I love slack, it's a straw-man) to get them to own the solution via something like <a href="http://www.mattermost.org/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow" class="external-link no-image">MatterMost</a>
; you need to do the leg work and setup an instance. Then you need to get it integrated into your life and ensure it's easy to use, be the best first review that you can be for the new replacement technology. Then, you need to start getting people signed up on the mattermost instance by proxy. Friends, colleagues, to share a file, to go "hey have you seen...". Little by little, in dribs and drabs, you'll start tapping into that well of social capital in order to get your organization to stop standardizing on Slack and move over to MatterMost.</p>
<p>What did people gain? Well, they still use a communication tool but maybe in this instance the surface  gain is in no longer paying Slack for a hosted instance. The social effects of this change could be far greater. Maybe without a paywall more people in the company can use the software. Maybe there's custom integration you can now write / pay for as a result of owning the technology. If the output to end users is the same, they won't question or review the additional impacts on the organization (no one questions things presented with a happy face).</p>
<p>Maybe now your writing your own code, owning the process in one area which has you turn inward and move more things in-house. Maybe people have a greater comprehension for the power of open source and look to you as an expert. The impacts are far greater then just what technology will we use today; what's the philosophy behind this decision?</p>
<p>Figure it out, own it, and spread it P2P.</p>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>item-818bd74d-1af8-6db0-3fb0-c1fe996c4f9d</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 15:29:48 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>