<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>btopro</title>
    <link>https://btopro.com/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Crazy, abrasive, caring, dreaming the future into existence.</description>
    <copyright>Copyright (C) 2019 https://btopro.com</copyright>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2019 12:13:08 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://btopro.com/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <item>
      <title>Why I started hax-camp</title>
      <link>https://btopro.com/why-i-started-hax-camp</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>Hi. I'm Bryan Ollendyke, and I have a vision of the future and, I think, a way to get there. I'm not fancy. I don't have big money. I don't have important people on high; I have something far more important than any big tech start up of today: <b>Belief</b>

.</p>
<p>I believe in the people around me. My coworkers, my friends, my colleagues that have seen what I've been talking about for years and didn't write me off. While many have helped put < <b>hax-camp ></b>
 on both financially and through time donation, I knew 2019 was the year to plant the flag in the ground and I'm honored to have so many say "Let's do this!".</p>
<p>I believe we can make a better world by improving education. And yes, I oddly believe a big piece of that can come through the smallest of things: a "cute" little text editor.</p>
<p>I'm not logical if you're viewing the world through the lens of today. But I'm not "playing" for the markets and systems of today, I'm playing for the markets and systems that will be to come. I'm not here to participate in the marketplace that exist, I'm here to bring us to another level; where we need to be pushing towards.</p>
<p>I think that the <i>web component standard</i>

 poses an existential threat to the monopoly on talent, power and capabilities previously only held by an elite few. I think this will become more and more understood as people dig into the elements our team has created thus far and the ones we have planned to create which invoke containers on demand to blur the lines of what "static" systems can do.</p>
<p>Take Drupal, a place I've called home for over a decade. Regularly you can pull $100 to $350 and hour for work because of the knowledge economy that's emerged there. That isn't equality. that isn't stability. Its rampant profiteering and a direct incentive to keep knowledge complex, locked away, and difficult to use.</p>
<p>Take traditional front end languages like React, places I'm critical of. They require tooling, advanced JavaScript knowledge, conventions that are non-standard and non-uniform across frameworks. These jobs pay in the $140k - $200k a year range and contract work isn't as lucrative as Drupal but still up there.</p>
<p>I can't teach the people around me React or how to leverage parts of React components in their Drupal backed CMS. I can't teach them how to write template code and grant them permission to edit these critical theme files just to render something on the page.</p>
<p>But I can teach them that if they copy and paste a < video - player > tag like below, it'll render the same way every time.</p>
<video-player iframed="iframed" is-a11y-media="is-a11y-media" is-youtube="is-youtube" lang="en" preload="metadata" source="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BnIIoedo9HA" source-type="youtube" sticky-corner="top-right" youtube-id="BnIIoedo9HA" schema-resource-id="#3ad05175-0f0a-9aa3-bd92" __utils="[object HTMLElement]" resource="#3ad05175-0f0a-9aa3-bd92" prefix="oer:http://oerschema.org/ schema:http://schema.org/ dc:http://purl.org/dc/terms/ foaf:http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/ cc:http://creativecommons.org/ns# bib:http://bib.schema.org " accent-color="grey" style="width: 75%; margin: 0px auto; display: block;" sources="[]" tracks="[]"></video-player>
<p>I can't teach them how to accessibly create a multiple-choice question in context of material in order to give more effective feedback and pacing to students. But I can have them put down a multiple-choice tag and expand the possibilities of education and learning beyond where they traditionally thought possible.</p>
<multiple-choice style="width: 100%;" title="Does this change everything?" check-label="Check answer" reset-label="Reset" question="When you can empower anyone to write and express themselves in complex ways, can that lead to societal change and a more robust form of conversation?" correct-text="You better believe it" incorrect-text="Try to believe." schema-resource-id="#69279b8a-babf-7bb2-bb73" accent-color="grey" resource="#69279b8a-babf-7bb2-bb73" prefix="oer:http://oerschema.org/ schema:http://schema.org/ dc:http://purl.org/dc/terms/ foaf:http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/ cc:http://creativecommons.org/ns# bib:http://bib.schema.org " typeof="oer:Assessment" answers="[{&quot;correct&quot;:true,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;Yes&quot;,&quot;userGuess&quot;:false},{&quot;correct&quot;:false,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;Maybe&quot;,&quot;userGuess&quot;:false},{&quot;correct&quot;:false,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;Your full of it&quot;,&quot;userGuess&quot;:false}]"></multiple-choice>
<p>I believe that the abstraction of advanced HTML, JavaScript and CSS in an intentional, compartmentalized way, has the ability to affect markets, empower people previously forgotten by technocratic overlords, so drunk on their own abilities that they don't realize how elite they've become; further dividing society into haves and have nots all while thinking they are solving the problem with the latest junket app.</p>
<p>I believe that together, we can begin to build enough reusable, platform and framework agnostic pieces, that we can build any application out visually with reduced complexity.</p>
<p>I believe that together, we can give people authoring experiences that are second to none, sustainable, and portable across environments and contexts.</p>
<p>I believe that together, we can all openly share and learn from one another and benefit from each other's experiences, successes and failures, regardless of who we are or where we come from.</p>
<p>I believe that together, platforms and framework wars aside, we can build a better tomorrow by putting down our shields and locking arms.</p>
<p>I believe in HAX and the potential of <b>< hax-camp ></b>



 so much that I've spent <i><b>my own money</b>



</i>



 to purchase over 40, customized hockey jerseys without logos or brands, to symbolize our variety, uniqueness and individuality of developers and platforms yet unified under one common platform.</p>
<p>I believe in HAX camp 2019 as the beginning of something new and the forging of a new path. <a href="https://www.eventbrite.com/e/hax-camp-web-components-all-the-things-tickets-69761529613?aff=escb&utm-source=cp&utm-term=listing&utm-campaign=social&utm-medium=discovery&utm-content=attendeeshare">Will you join us and start a new beginning together?</a>


</p>
<p><a href="https://hax.camp/">hax.camp</a>


</p>
<grid-plate layout="4/4/4" responsive-size="xl" style="width: 100%;"><img src="files/EBd7L7eXkAAOW_d.jpg" slot="col-1" style="width: 75%;"/>

<img src="files/IMG_20190729_213158.jpg" slot="col-3" style="width: 75%;"/><img src="files/IMG_20190819_205859.jpg" slot="col-3" style="width: 75%;"/>
<img src="files/IMG_20190729_213151.jpg" slot="col-1" style="width: 75%;"/><img src="files/IMG_20190729_103418.jpg" slot="col-2" style="width: 75%;"/><img src="files/IMG_20190726_105535.jpg" slot="col-3" style="width: 75%;"/><img src="files/IMG_20190726_110706.jpg" slot="col-2" style="width: 75%;"/><img src="files/IMG_20190716_102855.jpg" slot="col-1" style="width: 100%;"/></grid-plate>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>https://btopro.com/why-i-started-hax-camp</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2019 12:12:51 -0600</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My first time on stage</title>
      <link>https://btopro.com/my-first-time-on-stage</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[  ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>https://btopro.com/my-first-time-on-stage</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2019 13:09:43 -0600</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Annabella</title>
      <link>https://btopro.com/annabella</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[  ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>https://btopro.com/annabella</guid>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jul 2019 21:34:02 -0600</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hey, remember when</title>
      <link>https://btopro.com/hey-remember-when</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[  ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>https://btopro.com/hey-remember-when</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2019 18:45:49 -0600</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Open Community Pedagogy</title>
      <link>https://btopro.com/open-community-pedagogy</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[  ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>https://btopro.com/open-community-pedagogy</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2019 09:07:22 -0600</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stand against the ocean</title>
      <link>https://btopro.com/stand-against-the-ocean-1</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <meme-maker style="width: 75%; margin: 0px auto; display: block;" image-url="files/scale-50/IMG_20190307_142300.jpg" top-text="Stand Against" bottom-text="Complacency" imageurl="files/scale-50/IMG_20190307_142300.jpg" toptext="Stop what your doing" bottomtext="Stand and be counted" dataeditable="" datahaxray="Meme"></meme-maker>
<p>The waves of life will crash upon you, and they'll crash hard my son. You'll be expected to carry loads that you feel aren't yours. You'll be asked to stand when it's so much easier to sit. You'll be expected to behave, when rebellion is necessary.</p>
<p>When they tell you to sit, these forces of complacency, know that with each passing wave, you drift further from the goal back to shore. When we sit by the waters edge, deciding whether to wade into uncharted territory, we're hit with relentlessly strong currents.</p>
<p>The water seeks to pull us down to the depth below. To consume those that enter the unknown. If we step into the waters a few inches, get concerns and then merely sit still, we have to face the force of the crashing wave.</p>
<p>These waves are far stronger than we realize, each crash lifting you off your seat and shifting you back ever slightly, sometimes so little that we hardly notice. But rest assured, you are being pushed backward. If you sit long enough, the waves will push you back till your nearly on dry land; the journey over.</p>
<p>If you stand though, you'll be hit by those heavy waves. And you must be, for if not broken against the waves we harden and are made stronger. For we are anti-fragile my child. We were born to be strengthen with each passing wave.</p>
<p>If we step forward in between these waves, never ceasing, never resting but to achieve eternity, then we will be where we want to in this world. Out beyond the currents, beyond the waters of today. Stand my child and cut through the waves.</p>
<h2 class="hax-active">Be different.</h2>
<p>Be abnormal. <span style="font-size: var(--haxcms-base-styles-p-font-size, 24px); letter-spacing: var(--haxcms-base-styles-p-letter-spacing, 0.5px); caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">Be Bold. Live Free. Burn Bright. Never back down. Never surrender. Never let anyone tell you who you are not, show them who you are.</span></p>
<p>For if we all stand and cut through the waves, they become increasingly less difficult. The deeper the water gets, the less impactful the crashing of the waves.</p>
<p>And we may yet be able to swim to the brighter shores across the chasm we've been told exists but was never the reality.</p>
<hr style="width: 50%;"/><video-player accent-color="deep-purple" iframed="iframed" is-a11y-media="is-a11y-media" is-youtube="is-youtube" lang="en" media-title="The humbling river" preload="metadata" source="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=O0YxeTjFn70" source-type="youtube" sticky-corner="top-right" youtube-id="O0YxeTjFn70" resource="#2a70bb89-4959-afee-809a" prefix="oer:http://oerschema.org/ schema:http://schema.org/ dc:http://purl.org/dc/terms/ foaf:http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/ cc:http://creativecommons.org/ns# bib:http://bib.schema.org " sources="[]" tracks="[]" schema-resource-id="#2a70bb89-4959-afee-809a"></video-player>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>https://btopro.com/stand-against-the-ocean-1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2019 14:40:55 -0600</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EdTechJoker</title>
      <link>https://btopro.com/edtechjoker-1</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>Ex Plures Plures</p>
<p>From many, many. The phrase of a new publishing revolution.</p>
<p>I'm old enough to remember old me. Oh, that guy. So tired. So broken. So lost. So disaffected. But the guy that showed up at Domains19. That spoke with a burning passion about what he's doing, why he's doing it, and without fear. That guy is working towards who I want to be.</p>
<p>Sustaining momentum is a difficult beast in software projects, especially passion and mission driven ones. It takes recognition that hundreds of hours of work. Sleepless nights, broken builds, mis-named variables, enter and escape key pushes, all culminate in 5 minutes if your lucky, 5 seconds more than likely.</p>
<p>All that work. All that lost sleep, often the pain of which is detailed here in specific posts about losing time with my children to pursuit what I've been made to do, the person I want them to proud of some day.... boils down to those few minutes.</p>
<p>I've had "shots" before, times when I said "yes, this is it. this is the moment that people will understand the picture in my head. I'll explain it right <i>this</i>

 time. <b>This time they'll get it</b>

." A false fairytale that you'll ever wake up from; a scene in a movie and say there's the scene that they "made it".</p>
<p>Last year around this time is a perfect example; presenting to a New York based audience about HAX. Money to solve problems, audience receptive to headless solutions; and me with a system that gobbled our presenters content just hours before the talk. A tech demo blow up prior to what would be a tech talk disaster.</p>
<p>The co-presenters thought it went fine and talking to people after they generally got it. But I didn't want "generally got it". I wanted effect, impact, realization. And there I was.. with a broken "solution" projecting an alternative view of reality that didn't just look half baked but was.</p>
<p>It was painful. Really. deeply painful. To realize that I wasn't there yet. That I still had nothing to show for all my sleeplessness. I did another talk the next week and it was fine, much better but I didn't seek it to have this impact. I knew I had over hyped myself as to what would happen.</p>
<p>After those, I shifted gears to process. We shifted to internal workflow and process that needed realigned if we would ever make it there. It was demoralizing work; at times copy and paste, run a job that had to pass on 180 project repos in an unknown configuration taking upwards of an hour to process, failing if it didn't get every single one. We didn't know what we were doing, we just knew we had to regroup code organization wise.</p>
<p>But after two months, and having a process that appeared to finally be correct. I began the hard work of converting and normalizing all of our elements, our labor that was well intentioned but slightly off course if it would ever hit the quality standards of a production project / product.</p>
<p>I took a week several months ago and just normalized some doc blocks, some placement of basic syntax, demos, all the nitty gritty.</p>
<p>There are hundreds of hours. Painful, hours, that go into being able to pull off where we are now, and where we'll get to from here. It's all for those 5 minutes, those 5 seconds.</p>
<p>But to hear that spark. Those eyes light up. To see another human being you don't know or have just met connect with your work, your vision, for the first time... that's what I live for. I live for changing minds, teaching, helping empower others.</p>
<p>I have a very supportive wife and family; friends and colleagues too, all that I love. They got me through that darkness by believing that what I was saying was possible and picked me up either through coffee or venting or a drink after work or a goal on the hockey rink. They helped keep me from my darker parts.</p>
<p>But those new eyes. Those delights, those people we unplug form the matrix of what was. They aren't people I know. They aren't sold based on knowing me. They sometimes aren't deeply technical.</p>
<video-player accent-color="deep-purple" iframed is-a11y-media is-youtube lang="en" media-title="HAXTheWeb: Chaotic good" preload="metadata" source="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Eksr9y4nxQ4" sources="[]" source-type="youtube" sticky-corner="top-right" tracks="[]" youtube-id="Eksr9y4nxQ4" resource="#38020ce8-4c27-cdc1-9060" prefix="oer:http://oerschema.org/ schema:http://schema.org/ dc:http://purl.org/dc/terms/ foaf:http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/ cc:http://creativecommons.org/ns# bib:http://bib.schema.org "></video-player>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>https://btopro.com/edtechjoker-1</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jun 2019 20:14:21 -0600</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Technical weapons</title>
      <link>https://btopro.com/technical-weapons</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[  ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>https://btopro.com/technical-weapons</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2019 20:51:23 -0600</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I made a thing</title>
      <link>https://btopro.com/i-made-a-thing</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[  ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>https://btopro.com/i-made-a-thing</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 May 2019 15:01:29 -0600</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>THE web components high performance video</title>
      <link>https://btopro.com/the-web-components-high-performance-video-1</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>I've become a bit performance obsessed. I often lament that the worst part of working on something you are passionate about is that first impressions with the software are everything and that if someone isn't hooked visually in about 5 seconds, you're not going to get them interested in your work.</p>
<p>To that end, I've been performance obsessed in web components, <a href="https://haxtheweb.org/">HAXTheWeb</a>
, and all server configuration areas. I was able to take our scores previously from pretty bad to decent on Google Lighthouse, just by making some tweaks to how things rendered, timing, etc.</p>
<p>I neglected one factor in all my previous testing though... I wasn't actually using a live, running, out there in the open web server. It was always local development or github pages, which can only go so far on their own. I expected to get the same results when I pushed things up to a live server and ran some tests. Boy was I wrong...</p>
<h2>It was even faster in production!</h2>
<img src="files/scale-50/2019-05-24_11-14-49.jpg" alt="Insanely high scores on Google's Lighthouse appliance to demonstrate performance of up coming project." style="width: 100%; margin: 0px auto; display: block;"/><p>These rather insane scores are showing an upcoming <a href="https://github.com/elmsln/haxiam">SaaS version of HAXcms</a>
 that I'm currently building. Other team members reactions to playing with the SaaS offering recently have ranged from "I love you" to "I can't believe it's this far along" to "why is it this fast? This is stupid fast" to utter disbelief.</p>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/hey__mp">@hey__mp</a>
 opened our test site on his phone, on rural wifi (so DSL, and not good DSL) and had the site in 1 second. This HAXcms in production, is stupid fast. I decided to shoot a video talking about how we were able to achieve these stupidly fast scores given the following constraints we intentionally place on ourselves:</p>
<ul><li>We do not bundle assets, we ship ES6 modules / AMD directly to browsers</li>



<li>IE11 / things outside of ES6 window are shipped a watered down design</li>


<li>Users must click through a UI and build a site much like they would in a CMS context, yet the system produce a high scoring offline capable PWA (so no developers hands in the PWA construction)</li>


<li>We do not do server side rendering, it's all client side processed</li>


<li>All decisions are made to ensure HAXcms micro-sites can run with or without HAXcms as part of our publishing methodology (so all sites are decentralizable / copy and paste capable and run anywhere)</li>


</ul>
<p><span style="caret-color: rgb(0, 0, 0);">So given these constrains,... how the hell were we able to achieve these scores? I encourage you to watch and find out.</span></p>
<video-player accent-color="lime" dark="dark" iframed="" is-a11y-media="" is-youtube="" lang="en" media-title="Crazy deep performance walk through with HAXcms" preload="metadata" source="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7o8T1eymTnQ" source-type="youtube" sticky-corner="top-right" youtube-id="7o8T1eymTnQ" resource="#3e3cee5f-bc3f-b445-8b9f" prefix="oer:http://oerschema.org/ schema:http://schema.org/ dc:http://purl.org/dc/terms/ foaf:http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/ cc:http://creativecommons.org/ns# bib:http://bib.schema.org " sources="[]" tracks="[]"></video-player>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>https://btopro.com/the-web-components-high-performance-video-1</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2019 08:56:35 -0600</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ocean</title>
      <link>https://btopro.com/ocean</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[  ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>https://btopro.com/ocean</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2019 12:21:19 -0600</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Drunken UX interview</title>
      <link>https://btopro.com/drunken-ux-interview-1</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>I was recently interviewed on the <a href="https://drunkenux.com/podcast/33-hax-the-planet/">Drunken UX podcast</a>












, a show about all things web and user experience design. I was there to talk web components, block editors, and of course <a href="https://haxtheweb.org/">#HAXTheWeb</a>









.</p>
<p><br/></p>
<p>The conversation steered into the advantages of web components over past technology solutions and libraries and is a really good consolidation of a lot of my thoughts about web components and their importance in building a more sustainable, open web. Half way through we turn to HAX and I'm left open to rant... (so I do)</p>
<p>I'd like to unpack a statement because I realize that while I did an ok job of explaining it, I'd like to have it written down if it end sup coming up. I said something intentionally controversial because if we don't challenge those with power, regardless of their intention, then we are left accepting powerlessness as a feature instead of the bug that it is.</p>
<h2>The quote</h2>
<p>The takes place at 44:41 remaining in the show. <a href="https://drunkenux.com/podcast/">Please subscribe to, rate and review their podcast</a>












 but I wanted to link to the audio here in context in case you wanted to listen to it while reading why I feel this way.</p>
<paper-audio-player src="https://episodes.drunkenux.com/drunkenux/dux-e33.mp3" title="#33: HAX the Planet!" preload="auto" current-time="4036.446044" time-left="5387.833469" small-skip="15" large-skip="60" role="application" aria-label="Audio Player" aria-describedby="title" accent-color="purple" resource="#7b05d228-7263-fb95-435e" prefix="oer:http://oerschema.org/ schema:http://schema.org/ dc:http://purl.org/dc/terms/ foaf:http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/ cc:http://creativecommons.org/ns# bib:http://bib.schema.org " style="width: 75%; margin: 0px auto; display: block;"></paper-audio-player>
<lrndesign-blockquote citation="04/01/2019" image="files/crop-sm/IMG_20190127_153429.jpg" author="btopro" display-mode="leather" resource="#f2d9bcf3-7000-eacb-cf69" prefix="oer:http://oerschema.org/ schema:http://schema.org/ dc:http://purl.org/dc/terms/ foaf:http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/ cc:http://creativecommons.org/ns# bib:http://bib.schema.org " style="width: 100%; margin: 0px auto; display: block;">  <span>I see Gutenberg as a<br/>
<strong>direct existential threat</strong>












 to the open web [and OER].</span></lrndesign-blockquote>
<p>So this critique is not of the people who work on Gutenberg. It is a deeper philosophical question of trust and control in open source and the open web. When I say do you trust Matt. I don't mean as a person, I mean do you trust one person with control of your entire UX, forever.</p>
<p>It's a fair comparison to say the same could be lodged at me in designing HAX; and yes I am aware other people have worked on Gutenberg (and HAX has more then just me on it...). My primary criticisms grouped:</p>
<h2 class="hax-active">Sustainability</h2>
<p>React is the flavor of this five year segment of time and we're coming up on its end. Being from Drupal I saw core developers jump on javascript trains that had already fallen out of favor by the time they deployed. This will not be the case with web components. Web components are in the browser you're viewing this on. They aren't going away.</p>
<p>You may say "But React isn't going away" and that's reasonable. But I mean... jQuery didn't go anywhere... so why did we all move away from it for these advanced platforms? It's all "just" javascript right?</p>
<p>React's destiny is pegged to Facebook's desire for it; which means WordPress will have to keep pace with where they take that community. I don't view this as long term sustainable. Will a WordPress site site, without being touched, and still function correctly 10 years from now when needing to update the Gutenblocks as well as surrounding JS library ecosystem?</p>
<p>HAX output no longer requires HAX. Content pulled into HAX is just reading DOM and then processing it. We can disappear tomorrow and our elements will still work. Since we treat the DOM as an API, we will continue to expand it at a rate that far outpaces Gutenberg.</p>
<h2 class="hax-active">A story</h2>
<p>Our components work anywhere, with or without HAX. We make a public website (like this one you're viewing). As part of the build we make a new card element. It can go from usage on this website to generalized, HAX capable element in about 5 minutes. The web expands our platform, not WordPress. WordPress (Drupal too) will never keep pace with our expansion just given this fact.</p>
<p>As we build the web, we build up the base of legos for all of it. Not just specific pockets of it.</p>
<p>Accessibility</p>
<p>Gutenberg and accessibility have had a rocky time out of the gate. Learning React, just to participate in accessibility testing is a non-starter. We keep our web components compiled but not bundled in part for this reason. Anyone can run an accessibility audit on something we make, find the element in the DOM that wraps what failed, and make a report. They can also see the file it came from and trace it back to the source; which what they'll find...looks...like...html.</p>
<p>This may seem petty but it's not. We're actually at odds with the web component community standards (which is to roll things like Webpack / bundlers to reduce assets delivered). It's more important to us that anyone can find, diagnose, and remix what we're doing, and the traceability by the average web professional (not WP pro + React pro) is critical to long term sustainability.</p>
<p>HAX also originates in higher education, where we have <i><b>legal</b>











</i>











 and ethical responsibilities to generate, maintain and improve the accessibility of what we produce. Web components represent an immense opportunity for us to generate a more open and accessible web as a result of remix.</p>
<h2 class="hax-active">Power consolidation</h2>
<p>Please don't confuse charity with corporate interests. "OH THANK YOU FOR THIS EDITOR"... which you only produced because you need to in order to try and go after markets like Wix and Squarespace. The goal isn't democratizing the web anymore, it's consolidating power under one banner. Non-conspiratorially, the less people that understand the authoring experience of WordPress, the more business for WordPress.com and vendor space.</p>
<p>Our component library is highly readable, has tooling (and soon front end assets) to completely automate the writing of the wiring for our editor. Editor outputs are no longer tied to the editor; we seek a great rebalancing of the powers of the web. HAX has ties into multiple CMS ecosystems already and can easily be ported over to others.</p>
<p>Yes, we're building a "CMS" to manage pages because the editor eliminates the vast majority of needs for database driven anything. Yes, I'll continue to criticize database backed solutions (while still having to maintain my own slew of them). However, HAXcms will be completely built out of open and reusable components that aside from our theme scaffolding will make sense in other solutions (that are non-HAX). We are actively tearing down power structures in the methodologies by which we are approaching development.</p>
<p>We publish all our components to webcomponents.org, a public, non-CMS specific location. I've seen talk of WP having its own Blocks catalog, which makes sense... but again, why consolidate UX discovery to one ecosystem. Why develop for a single ecosystem when you can improve the web holistically?</p>
<h2>Not being a jerk.</h2>
<p>Gutenberg is a fantastic idea with a lot of effort and resources and sleepless nights poured into it. It will empower people to produce things and is open source and those are great things. I think it threatens long term sustainability, accessibility, and development interest. I think web components provide a unique opportunity to tear down the power silos we've all built over the last decade.</p>
<p>You shouldn't need someone else in order to present yourself online. It shouldn't cost you anything. You should have total ownership and control over your information. It shouldn't be tied to any platform beyond the browser itself.</p>
<p>We have a unique opportunity to ensure that happens. <span style="caret-color: var(--hax-color-text);">Don't throw your efforts into a single silo that will let you down.</span></p>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>https://btopro.com/drunken-ux-interview-1</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2019 11:47:45 -0600</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>All screens have rights</title>
      <link>https://btopro.com/all-screens-have-rights-1</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <p>The <a href="https://www.engadget.com/2019/03/26/european-parliament-copyright-directive-article-13/">EU recently passed Article 13</a>





, which it's still too early to tell the implications of but it's troubling to say the least. Any time people start trying to legislate 1s and 0s I get concerned; namely, because their interests are in direct competition with those of their citizens (governments enjoy having major international enterprises they can sue to fill their coffers after all).</p>
<p>That whole thing had me thinking about access to information and the ideas of <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2013/01/13/technology/aaron-swartz-internet-activist-dies-at-26.html">Aaron Swartz</a>





; namely that information seeks to be free. In the years since Aaron's unfortunate death, we've seen silicon valley accelerate in its quest to put up barriers to the free flow of information in the name of a new enemy: User Experience.</p>
<p>Facebook: "We have the best experiences, and so you should <i><b>share</b>





</i>





 all your content here without thinking about it"<br/>Twitter: "We have the fastest experience, so you should <i><b>share</b>





</i>





 your stream of consciousness here without thinking about it"<br/>Medium: "We have the best writing experience, so you should share your ideas here while working them out."<br/></p>
<p>These platforms. These digital silos, do empower people to share and have a voice. But they are antithetical to the open content and open access vision that Aaron is often credited with.</p>
<p>I was passed along some links recently related to <a href="https://indieweb.org/">Indieweb</a>





 and <a href="https://ioo.coop/">The Internet of Ownership</a>





, and it got me thinking. HAX and HAXcms are in this sphere of local control, better control, better tools, more access to those tools, but I haddn't really thought through the additional technical requirements not talked about in that pursuit. Namely, that every screen has a right to content.</p>
<h2 class="hax-active">Extending the vision of Information seeks to be Free</h2>
<p>Every screen you possess has a right to access content. If you are connected to the internet, there should be no barriers between that screen and web based HTML data structures... otherwise known as all information that exists on the internet.</p>
<p>Every site you access adopts the web platform standards.. with a catch.</p>
<h3 class="hax-active">Click here to upgrade your app?</h3>
<p><i>Not using Chrome? Click here to switch</i>





</p>
<p><i>You appear to be using an outdated browser, please upgrade.</i>





</p>
<p>Now look, upgrading, and modernizing with the web are nice. Helpful especially to the developer. But if we as developers</p>
<p>Every screens have a right to content. The internet has given birth to incredible communications possibilities (duh). But in that rise, we've seen an ebb and flow as far as access to content, ideas and media. Facebook, twitter and others require you to use updated devices and software in order to access their platform.</p>
<h3>I'm sorry let's reframe that</h3>
<p>Facebook, twitter and others require you to upgrade and pay additional monies for modern, fancy devices, <b>in order to read and express ideas with one another.</b>





</p>
<p>The platforms require you to use them and manipulate you into using them more. They connect you to people but at a price; that you will always connect through them. One of the major methods of dissolving decentralized individual ownership of the web was by killing RSS.</p>
<p>Google played a huge role in this through killing it's podcasting platform; and not that they controlled the universe in this regard, but it forced content producers to think of other ways of doing syndication. Namely, through Google and Apple app stores.</p>
<h2 class="hax-active">We want to bring the old web back</h2>
<p>And here's the plan. Beyond just HAX and HAXcms, its important to realize the philosophical design decisions that have now been baked into the HAXcms platform which I'll list as features in headings below.</p>
<h3 class="hax-active">Automatic RSS and Atom feed generation</h3>
<p>RSS and Atom allow sites to share updates about what's been produced. It is (an old) format that is a pure form of notifying others sites about your latest postings and work. HAXcms now automatically generates these data feeds and then provides buttons for designers that automatically wire them up. This will let more people start publishing in these formats without having to think about it or know they exist.</p>
<h3 class="hax-active">Automatic sitemap / robots generation</h3>
<p>For search engines to find you, you need good SEO. HAXcms outputs with SEO best practices automatically baked into the platform. Again, you shouldn't have to think about getting high search rankings in order to do it. It should just happen.</p>
<h3 class="hax-active">Automatic Offline / lack of internet usage</h3>
<p>All HAXcms sites are what is known as "Progressive Web Apps" (PWA). A PWA can leverage modern browser techniques to allow users to install your website on their phone (or laptop), which improves performance and makes reading more enjoyable. Also, if a user has been to your website (installed or not) and loses internet connection, they'll still have access to all of the content of your site (minus things like remotely loaded images / links to other websites). This ensures a high quality experience even when internet is of low quality (big for rural, low income, mass transit or otherwise lacking in data connection users).</p>
<h3 class="hax-active">Support for all screens</h3>
<p>This was a tricky one. HAXcms is now able to deliver to all platforms of the web going back to <i>IE6 / FF 3 / Safari 4</i>




, possibly even earlier. For reference, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_Explorer_6">IE6 is 20 years old</a>

 . In order to achieve this, we've implemented a (brilliant) progressive enhancement strategy that works like so:</p>
<ul><li>Modern / evergreen? You get the highest quality, fastest method of shipping assets to you (~85% traffic)</li>





<li>Slightly behind / off version? You get the same quality, slightly slower to load (ES5 versions, still works great tho. ~8% traffic)</li>


<li>Edge / semi-modern but not web components native platforms - You get an alternate experience though still web components (~4%)</li>





<li>IE 6 - 11 / Anything made in the last 20 years, or has javascript disabled (~3% or less). You get an iframe / dramatically simplified version of the site. Web components in content won't work, but you'll still get all the images and text of the website.</li>





</ul>
<p> This approach will let us hit <b><i>effectively 100% of global web traffic with content</i>





</b>





, without changing the workflow of you, the publisher. Own you content. Own your experience. HAX the current market that has forced us all to require they exist in order to have a voice. <a href="https://haxtheweb.org/">HAXTheWeb</a>





.</p>
<p>Here are screenshots of IE6, Safari 4, iPad2, Android 2.2 and Firefox 3 of this site!</p>
<img src="files/safari4.jpg" style="width: 75%;"/><img src="files/ff3.jpg" style="width: 75%;"/><img src="files/android22.jpg" style="width: 25%;"/><img src="files/ipad2.jpg" style="width: 50%;"/><img src="files/ie6.jpg" style="width: 100%;"/> ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>https://btopro.com/all-screens-have-rights-1</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2019 09:24:37 -0600</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reclaim the web</title>
      <link>https://btopro.com/reclaim-the-web</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[  ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>https://btopro.com/reclaim-the-web</guid>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2019 08:36:23 -0600</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HAXcms Theme layer Code Review</title>
      <link>https://btopro.com/haxcms-theme-layer-code-review-1</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <h2 class="hax-active">Weekly Code Review</h2>
<p class="hax-active">This 1 starts to get pretty interesting. The team talks about HAXcms, ideates about the new capabilities of the theme layer. This gets into code and great discussion of intentions surrounding it / needs</p>
<video-player accent-color="light-green" dark="dark" lang="en" preload="metadata" source="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZZIE7oCcM_Q&feature=youtu.be" sticky-corner="top-right" youtube-id="ZZIE7oCcM_Q?feature=youtu.be" iframed="" source-type="youtube" is-a11y-media="" is-youtube="" media-title="HAXcms - Theme layer discussion" style="width: 75%; margin: 0px auto; display: block;"></video-player>
<p>We start getting into what we can add to the theme layer and the JSON object structure we're using could be extended to effectively bring content types and field APIs to HAXcms while keeping life relative to a small JSON format. It's a bit ridiculous how fast this system is.<br/></p>
<p>I talk through the developer theme, slide player, and kick around ideas for what can come next and then <a href="https://twitter.com/hey__mp">@hey__MP</a>

 and <a href="https://twitter.com/cgldevel">@CGLDevel</a>

 show their progress on on a custom theme they're developing for <b><a href="https://haxtheweb.org/">HAXcms</a>

</b>

 which will start to reshape minds about what this is and is possible.<br/></p>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/nikkimk">@NikkiMK</a>

 closes us out by showing how her new rich-text-editor tag is coming along as well as explaining to Chuck (and anyone watching) why we're working on two text editors simultaneously.<br/></p>
<h2>I. Love. This. Team.</h2>
<p>The video closes the way I really feel. I. Love. This. Team.</p>
<p>Keep pushing gang, we're building something amazing that will change the world.</p>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>https://btopro.com/haxcms-theme-layer-code-review-1</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 13:13:35 -0700</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ELMS:LN Code review series Part 1</title>
      <link>https://btopro.com/elms-ln-code-review-series-part-1-1</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[ <grid-plate style="width: 100%;" breakpoint-sm="900" breakpoint-md="1200" breakpoint-lg="1500" breakpoint-xl="1800" columns="2" layout="1:1" responsive-size="xs">  <h2 slot="col-1">Going to get really meta here..</h2>






  <p slot="col-1">This is a video showing how this blog post was made. The post follows but this video shows the state of HAXcms which is the system being used to develop this blog and haxtheweb.org and... effectively anything.</p>

<p slot="col-1">The state management in HAXcms is dramatically improved from a few weeks ago and the editing experience in HAXeditor is becoming increasingly more fluid and robust.</p>






  <video-player accent-color="blue" dark="dark" lang="en" preload="metadata" source="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=V8UQOo5d4LQ" sticky-corner="top-right" youtube-id="V8UQOo5d4LQ?undefined" iframed="" source-type="youtube" is-a11y-media="" is-youtube="" media-title="Video showing how this blog post was made" slot="col-2"></video-player>







</grid-plate>
<p><br/></p>
<p>This is to let you all know, that we've got a new "podcast" if you will that will give you a window into our world. Check out <a href="https://github.com/elmsln/hangouts">ELMS:LN hangouts on github</a>








.</p>
<video-player accent-color="teal" lang="en" preload="metadata" source="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o55m5yfdF-o" sticky-corner="top-right" youtube-id="o55m5yfdF-o?undefined" iframed="" source-type="youtube" is-a11y-media="" is-youtube="" media-title="ELMS:LN Code Review - Episode 1" style="width: 75%; margin: 0px auto; display: block;"></video-player>
<p>Here's the <a href="https://github.com/elmsln/hangouts/blob/master/2019/02.11.md">show notes from episode one</a>






:</p>
<md-block source="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/elmsln/hangouts/master/2019/02.11.md" style="width: 100%; margin: 0px auto; display: block;"></md-block>
 ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>https://btopro.com/elms-ln-code-review-series-part-1-1</guid>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 09:37:33 -0700</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fortify</title>
      <link>https://btopro.com/fortify</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[  ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>https://btopro.com/fortify</guid>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Feb 2019 21:36:07 -0700</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ministry of information</title>
      <link>https://btopro.com/ministry-of-information</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[  ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>https://btopro.com/ministry-of-information</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jan 2019 21:53:20 -0700</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Birthday party</title>
      <link>https://btopro.com/birthday-party</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[  ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>https://btopro.com/birthday-party</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jan 2019 21:53:20 -0700</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Creating the decentralized instructional experience app</title>
      <link>https://btopro.com/creating-the-decentralized-instructional-experience-app</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[  ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>https://btopro.com/creating-the-decentralized-instructional-experience-app</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jan 2019 21:53:20 -0700</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using Webcomponents to unearth the NGDLE</title>
      <link>https://btopro.com/using-webcomponents-to-unearth-the-ngdle</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[  ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>https://btopro.com/using-webcomponents-to-unearth-the-ngdle</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jan 2019 21:53:20 -0700</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>This is not reality</title>
      <link>https://btopro.com/this-is-not-reality</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[  ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>https://btopro.com/this-is-not-reality</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jan 2019 21:53:20 -0700</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Playing for 40</title>
      <link>https://btopro.com/playing-for-40</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[  ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>https://btopro.com/playing-for-40</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jan 2019 21:53:20 -0700</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dood</title>
      <link>https://btopro.com/dood</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[  ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>https://btopro.com/dood</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jan 2019 21:53:20 -0700</pubDate>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generation Uine</title>
      <link>https://btopro.com/generation-uine</link>
      <description>
          <![CDATA[  ]]>
      </description>
      <category></category>
      <guid>https://btopro.com/generation-uine</guid>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jan 2019 21:53:20 -0700</pubDate>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>